<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mteval>
<srcset setid="iwslt2012-tst2012" srclang="english">
<doc docid="1411" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/jack_choi_on_the_virtual_dissection_table.html</url> 
<description>Onstage at TED2012, Jack Choi demonstrates a powerful tool for training medical students: a stretcher-sized multi-touch screen of the human body that lets you explore, dissect and understand the body's parts and systems.</description> 
<keywords>education,health care,interface design,medical research,technology</keywords> 
<talkid>1411</talkid> 
<title>Jack Choi: On the virtual dissection table</title> 
<seg id="1"> You know, cadaver dissection is the traditional way of learning human anatomy.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> For students, it's quite an experience, but for a school, it could be very difficult or expensive to maintain.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> So we learned the majority of anatomic classes taught, they do not have a cadaver dissection lab.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> Maybe those reasons, or depending on where you are, cadavers may not be easily available.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> So to address this, we developed with a Dr. Brown in Stanford: virtual dissection table.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> So we call this Anatomage Table.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> So with this Anatomage Table, students can experience the dissection without a human cadaver.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> And the table form is important, and since it's touch-interactive, just like the way they do dissections in the lab, or furthermore just the way a surgeon operates on a patient you can literally interact with your table.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> Our digital body is one-to-one life size, so this is exactly the way students will see the real anatomy.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> I'm going to do some demonstrations.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> As you can see, I use my finger to interact with my digital body.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> I'm going to do some cuts.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> I can cut any way I want to, so I cut right here.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> Then it's going to show inside.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> And I can change my cut to see different parts.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> Maybe I can cut there, see the brain, and I can change my cut.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> You can see some internal organs.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> So we call this the slicer mode.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> OK, I'm going to do another cut.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> Right there.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> This shows a lot of internal structures.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> So if I want to see the back side, I can flip and see from behind.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> Like this.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> So if these images are uncomfortable to you or disturbing to you, that means we did the right job.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> So our doctors said these are eye candies.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> So instead of just butchering the body, I'd like to do more clinically meaningful dissections.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> What I'm going to do is I'm going to peel off all the skin, muscles and bones, just to see a few internal organs.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> Right here.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> Let's say I'm going to cut the liver right here.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> OK.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> Let's say I'm interested in looking at the heart.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> I'm going to do some surgery here.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> I'm going to cut some veins, arteries. Oops! ...  </seg>
<seg id="34"> You don't want to hear "oops" in real surgery.  </seg>
<seg id="35">  But fortunately, our digital man has "undo."  </seg>
<seg id="36">  OK.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> All right then.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> Let me zoom in.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> I'm going to make a cut right there.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> And then you can see the inside of the heart.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> You can see the atrium and the ventricles, how blood flows to our arteries and veins.  </seg>
<seg id="42"> Just like this, students can isolate anybody and dissect any way you want to.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> It doesn't have to be always dissection.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> Since it's digital, we can do reverse dissection.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> So let me show you, I'm going to start with the skeletal structure, and I can add a few internal organs.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> Yep.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> Maybe I can add quickly this way.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> And I can build muscles gradually, just like that.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> We can see tendons and muscles.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> Wish I could build my muscle this fast.  </seg>
<seg id="51">  And this is another way to learn anatomy.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> Another thing I can show you is, more often than not, doctors get to meet patients in X-ray form.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> So, Anatomage Table shows exactly how the anatomy will appear in X-ray.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> You can also interact with your X-ray, and also if you want, you can compare with how anatomy would appear in X-ray, too.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> So when you are done, just bring back the body and then it's ready for another session.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> It looks like our table also can transform gender, too.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> It's a female now.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> So this is Anatomage Table. Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1416" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/frank_warren_half_a_million_secrets.html</url> 
<description>"Secrets can take many forms -- they can be shocking, or silly, or soulful." Frank Warren, the founder of PostSecret.com, shares some of the half-million secrets that strangers have mailed him on postcards.</description> 
<keywords>arts,creativity,design,memory,storytelling</keywords> 
<talkid>1416</talkid> 
<title>Frank Warren: Half a million secrets</title> 
<seg id="1"> Hi, my name is Frank, and I collect secrets.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> It all started with a crazy idea in November of 2004.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> I printed up 3,000 self-addressed postcards, just like this.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> They were blank on one side, and on the other side I listed some simple instructions.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> I asked people to anonymously share an artful secret they'd never told anyone before.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> And I handed out these postcards randomly on the streets of Washington, D.C., not knowing what to expect.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> But soon the idea began spreading virally.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> People began to buy their own postcards and make their own postcards.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> I started receiving secrets in my home mailbox, not just with postmarks from Washington, D.C., but from Texas, California, Vancouver, New Zealand, Iraq.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> Soon my crazy idea didn't seem so crazy.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> PostSecret.com is the most visited advertisement-free blog in the world.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> And this is my postcard collection today.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> You can see my wife struggling to stack a brick of postcards on a pyramid of over a half-million secrets.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> What I'd like to do now is share with you a very special handful of secrets from that collection, starting with this one.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> "I found these stamps as a child, and I have been waiting all my life to have someone to send them to.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> I never did have someone." Secrets can take many forms.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> They can be shocking or silly or soulful.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> They can connect us to our deepest humanity or with people we'll never meet.  </seg>
<seg id="19">  Maybe one of you sent this one in.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> I don't know.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> This one does a great job of demonstrating the creativity that people have when they make and mail me a postcard.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> This one obviously was made out of half a Starbucks cup with a stamp and my home address written on the other side.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> "Dear Birthmother, I have great parents.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> I've found love. I'm happy." Secrets can remind us of the countless human dramas, of frailty and heroism, playing out silently in the lives of people all around us even now.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> "Everyone who knew me before 9/11 believes I'm dead." "I used to work with a bunch of uptight religious people, so sometimes I didn't wear panties, and just had a big smile and chuckled to myself."  This next one takes a little explanation before I share it with you.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> I love to speak on college campuses and share secrets and the stories with students.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> And sometimes afterwards I'll stick around and sign books and take photos with students.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> And this next postcard was made out of one of those photos.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> And I should also mention that, just like today, at that PostSecret event, I was using a wireless microphone.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> "Your mic wasn't off during sound check.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> We all heard you pee."  This was really embarrassing when it happened, until I realized it could have been worse.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> Right. You know what I'm saying.  </seg>
<seg id="33">  "Inside this envelope is the ripped up remains of a suicide note I didn't use.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> I feel like the happiest person on Earth " "One of these men is the father of my son.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> He pays me a lot to keep it a secret."  "That Saturday when you wondered where I was, well, I was getting your ring.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> It's in my pocket right now." I had this postcard posted on the PostSecret blog two years ago on Valentine's Day.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> It was the very bottom, the last secret in the long column.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> And it hadn't been up for more than a couple hours before I received this exuberant email from the guy who mailed me this postcard.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> And he said, "Frank, I've got to share with you this story that just played out in my life." He said, "My knees are still shaking."  </seg>
<seg id="40"> He said, "For three years, my girlfriend and I, we've made it this Sunday morning ritual to visit the PostSecret blog together and read the secrets out loud.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> I read some to her, she reads some to me."  </seg>
<seg id="42"> He says, "It's really brought us closer together through the years.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> And so when I discovered that you had posted my surprise proposal to my girlfriend at the very bottom, I was beside myself.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> And I tried to act calm, not to give anything away.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> And just like every Sunday, we started reading the secrets out loud to each other."  </seg>
<seg id="46"> He said, "But this time it seemed like it was taking her forever to get through each one." But she finally did.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> She got to that bottom secret, his proposal to her.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> And he said, "She read it once and then she read it again."  </seg>
<seg id="49"> And she turned to him and said, "Is that our cat?"  And when she saw him, he was down on one knee, he had the ring out.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> He popped the question, she said yes. It was a very happy ending.  </seg>
<seg id="51"> So I emailed him back and I said, "Please share with me an image, something, that I can share with the whole PostSecret community and let everyone know your fairy tale ending."  </seg>
<seg id="52"> And he emailed me this picture.  </seg>
<seg id="53">  "I found your camera at Lollapalooza this summer.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> I finally got the pictures developed and I'd love to give them to you." This picture never got returned back to the people who lost it, but this secret has impacted many lives, starting with a student up in Canada named Matty.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> Matty was inspired by that secret to start his own website, a website called IFoundYourCamera. Matty invites people to mail him digital cameras that they've found, memory sticks that have been lost with orphan photos.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> And Matty takes the pictures off these cameras and posts them on his website every week.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> And people come to visit to see if they can identify a picture they've lost or help somebody else get the photos back to them that they might be desperately searching for.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> This one's my favorite.  </seg>
<seg id="59">  Matty has found this ingenious way to leverage the kindness of strangers.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> And it might seem like a simple idea, and it is, but the impact it can have on people's lives can be huge.  </seg>
<seg id="61"> Matty shared with me an emotional email he received from the mother in that picture.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> "That's me, my husband and son.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> The other pictures are of my very ill grandmother.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> Thank you for making your site.  </seg>
<seg id="65"> These pictures mean more to me than you know.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> My son's birth is on this camera.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> He turns four tomorrow." Every picture that you see there and thousands of others have been returned back to the person who lost it -- sometimes crossing oceans, sometimes going through language barriers.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> This is the last postcard I have to share with you today.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> "When people I love leave voicemails on my phone I always save them in case they die tomorrow and I have no other way of hearing their voice ever again." When I posted this secret, dozens of people sent voicemail messages from their phones, sometimes ones they'd been keeping for years, messages from family or friends who had died.  </seg>
<seg id="70"> They said that by preserving those voices and sharing them, it helped them keep the spirit of their loved ones alive.  </seg>
<seg id="71"> One young girl posted the last message she ever heard from her grandmother.  </seg>
<seg id="72"> Secrets can take many forms.  </seg>
<seg id="73"> They can be shocking or silly or soulful.  </seg>
<seg id="74"> They can connect us with our deepest humanity or with people we'll never meet again.  </seg>
<seg id="75">  First saved voice message.  </seg>
<seg id="76">   It's somebody's birthday today   Somebody's birthday today   The candles are lighted   on somebody's cake   And we're all invited   for somebody's sake  You're 21 years old today.  </seg>
<seg id="77"> Have a real happy birthday, and I love you.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> I'll say bye for now.  </seg>
<seg id="79">  Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1413" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lucy_mcrae_how_can_technology_transform_the_human_body.html</url> 
<description>TED Fellow Lucy McRae is a body architect -- she imagines ways to merge biology and technology in our own bodies. In this visually stunning talk, she shows her work, from clothes that recreate the body's insides for a music video with pop-star Robyn, to a pill that, when swallowed, lets you sweat perfume.</description> 
<keywords>architecture,design,technology</keywords> 
<talkid>1413</talkid> 
<title>Lucy McRae: How can technology transform the human body?</title> 
<seg id="1"> I call myself a body architect.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> I trained in classical ballet and have a background in architecture and fashion.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> As a body architect, I fascinate with the human body and explore how I can transform it.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> I worked at Philips Electronics in the far-future design research lab, looking 20 years into the future.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> I explored the human skin, and how technology can transform the body.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> I worked on concepts like an electronic tattoo, which is augmented by touch, or dresses that blushed and shivered with light.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> I started my own experiments.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> These were the low-tech approaches to the high-tech conversations I was having.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> These are Q-tips stuck to my roommate with wig glue.  </seg>
<seg id="10">  I started a collaboration with a friend of mine, Bart Hess -- he doesn't normally look like this -- and we used ourselves as models.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> We transformed our apartments into our laboratories, and worked in a very spontaneous and immediate way.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> We were creating visual imagery provoking human evolution.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> Whilst I was at Philips, we discussed this idea of a maybe technology, something that wasn't either switched on or off, but in between.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> A maybe that could take the form of a gas or a liquid.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> And I became obsessed with this idea of blurring the perimeter of the body, so you couldn't see where the skin ended and the near environment started.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> I set up my studio in the red-light district and obsessively wrapped myself in plumbing tubing, and found a way to redefine the skin and create this dynamic textile.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> I was introduced to Robyn, the Swedish pop star, and she was also exploring how technology coexists with raw human emotion.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> And she talked about how technology with these new feathers, this new face paint, this punk, the way that we identify with the world, and we made this music video.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> I'm fascinated with the idea of what happens when you merge biology with technology, and I remember reading about this idea of being able to reprogram biology, in the future, away from disease and aging.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> And I thought about this concept of,  </seg>
<seg id="21"> imagine if we could reprogram our own body odor, modify and biologically enhance it, and how would that change the way that we communicate with each other?  </seg>
<seg id="22"> Or the way that we attract sexual partners?  </seg>
<seg id="23"> And would we revert back to being more like animals, more primal modes of communication?  </seg>
<seg id="24"> I worked with a synthetic biologist, and I created a swallowable perfume, which is a cosmetic pill that you eat and the fragrance comes out through the skin's surface when you perspire.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> It completely blows apart the way that perfume is, and provides a whole new format.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> It's perfume coming from the inside out.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> It redefines the role of skin, and our bodies become an atomizer.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> I've learned that there's no boundaries, and if I look at the evolution of my work i can see threads and connections that make sense.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> But when I look towards the future, the next project is completely unknown and wide open.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> I feel like I have all these ideas existing embedded inside of me, and it's these conversations and these experiences that connect these ideas, and they kind of instinctively come out.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> As a body architect, I've created this limitless and boundless platform for me to discover whatever I want.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> And I feel like I've just got started.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> So here's to another day at the office.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1422" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/drew_curtis_how_i_beat_a_patent_troll.html</url> 
<description>Drew Curtis, the founder of fark.com, tells the story of how he fought a lawsuit from a company that had a patent, "...for the creation and distribution of news releases via email." Along the way he shares some nutty statistics about the growing legal problem of frivolous patents.</description> 
<keywords>business,entrepreneur,law</keywords> 
<talkid>1422</talkid> 
<title>Drew Curtis: How I beat a patent troll</title> 
<seg id="1"> Last January, my company, Fark.com, was sued along with Yahoo, MSN, Reddit, AOL, TechCrunch and others by a company called Gooseberry Natural Resources.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> Gooseberry owned a patent for the creation and distribution of news releases via email.  </seg>
<seg id="3">  Now it may seem kind of strange that such a thing can actually be patented, but it does happen all the time.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> Take something already being done and patent it for an emerging technology -- like phone calls on the internet or video listings for TV shows or radio but for cellphones, and so on.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> The problem with these patents is that the mechanisms are obscure and the patent system is dysfunctional, and as a result, most of these lawsuits end in settlements.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> And because these settlements are under a non-disclosure agreement, no one knows what the terms were.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> And as a result, the patent troll can claim that they won the case.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> In the case of Gooseberry Natural Resources, this patent on emailing news releases had sort of a fatal flaw as it pertained to myself, and that was that in the mainstream media world there is only one definition for news release, and it turns out that is press release -- as in P.R.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> Now my company, Fark, deals with news, ostensibly, and as a result we were not in violation of this patent.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> So case closed, right?  </seg>
<seg id="11"> Wrong.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> One of the major problems with patent law is that, in the case that when you are sued by a patent troll, the burden of proof that you did not infringe on the patent is actually on the defendant, which means you have to prove that you do not infringe on the patent they're suing you on.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> And this can take quite a while.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> You need to know that the average patent troll defense costs two million dollars and takes 18 months when you win.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> That is your best case outcome when you get sued by a patent troll.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> Now I had hoped to team up with some of these larger companies in order to defend against this lawsuit, but one-by-one they settled out of the case, even though -- and this is important -- none of these companies infringed on this patent -- not a one of them.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> And they started settling out.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> The reason they settled out is because it's cheaper to settle than to fight the lawsuit -- clearly, two million dollars cheaper in some cases, and much worse if you actually lose.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> It would also constitute a massive distraction for management of a company, especially a small eight-man shop like my company.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> Six months into the lawsuit, we finally reached the discovery phase.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> And in discovery phase, we asked the patent troll to please provide screenshots of Fark where the infringement of their patent was actually occurring.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> Now perhaps it's because no such screenshots actually existed, but suddenly Gooseberry wanted to settle.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> Their attorney: "Ah, yes. My company's having a reorganization on our end."  </seg>
<seg id="24"> Never mind the fact that the address led to a strip mall somewhere in Northern L.A. with no employees.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> "And we'd like to go ahead and close this out.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> So would you mind giving us your best and final offer?" My response: "How about nothing?!"  We didn't have high hopes for that outcome.  </seg>
<seg id="27">  But they settled.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> No counter offer.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> Now, as mentioned before, one of the reasons I can talk to you about this is because there's no non-disclosure agreement on this case.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> Now how did that happen?  </seg>
<seg id="31"> Well during the settlement process, when we received our copy, I struck it.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> My attorney said, "Nah, no chance of that working."  </seg>
<seg id="33"> It came back signed.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> Now why? You can call them.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> They're not under NDA either.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> Now what did I learn from this case? Well, three things.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> First of all, if you can, don't fight the patent, fight the infringement.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> Patents are very difficult to overturn.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> Infringement is a lot easier to disprove.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> Secondly, make it clear from the beginning that either you have no money at all or that you would rather spend money with your attorney fighting the troll than actually giving them the money.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> Now the reason this works is because patent trolls are paid a percentage of what they're able to recover in settlements.  </seg>
<seg id="42"> If it becomes clear to them that they cannot recover any money, they become less interested in pursuing the case.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> Finally, make sure that you can tell them that you will make this process as annoying and as painful and as difficult as possible for them.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> Now this is a tactic that patent trolls are supposed to use on people to get their way.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> It turns out, because they're paid on contingency, it works really, really well in reverse.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> Don't forget that.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> So what does all this mean?  </seg>
<seg id="48"> Well to sum up, it boils down to one thing: Don't negotiate with terrorists.  </seg>
<seg id="49">  Patent trolls have done more damage to the United States economy than any domestic or foreign terrorist organization in history every year.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> And what do they do with that money?  </seg>
<seg id="51"> They plow it right back into filing more troll lawsuits.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> Now this is the point in the Talk where I'm supposed to come up with some kind of a solution for the patent system.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> And the problem with that is that there are two very large industry groups that have different outcomes in mind for the patent system.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> The health care industry would like stronger protections for inventors.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> The hi-tech industry would like stronger protections for producers.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> And these goals aren't necessarily diametrically opposed, but they are at odds.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> And as a result, patent trolls can kind of live in the space in between.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> So unfortunately I'm not smart enough to have a solution for the patent troll problem.  </seg>
<seg id="59"> However, I did have this idea, and it was kind of good.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> And I thought, "I should patent this."  </seg>
<seg id="61">  Behold, patent infringement via mobile device -- defined as a computer which is not stationary.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> My solution: award me this patent and I will troll them out of existence.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1417" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/frans_de_waal_do_animals_have_morals.html</url> 
<description>Empathy, cooperation, fairness and reciprocity -- caring about the well-being of others seems like a very human trait. But Frans de Waal shares some surprising videos of behavioral tests, on primates and other mammals, that show how many of these moral traits all of us share.</description> 
<keywords>animals,community,morality,science</keywords> 
<talkid>1417</talkid> 
<title>Frans de Waal: Moral behavior in animals</title> 
<seg id="1"> I was born in Den Bosch, where the painter Hieronymus Bosch named himself after.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> And so I've always been very fond of this painter who lived and worked in the 15th century.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> And what is interesting about him in relation to morality is that he lived at a time where religion's influence was waning, and he was sort of wondering, I think, what would happen with society if there was no religion or if there was less religion.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> And so he painted this famous painting, "The Garden of Earthly Delights," which some have interpreted as being humanity before the Fall, or being humanity without any Fall at all.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> And so it makes you wonder, what would happen if we hadn't tasted the fruit of knowledge, so to speak, and what kind of morality would we have?  </seg>
<seg id="6"> Much later, as a student, I went to a very different garden, a zoological garden in Arnhem where we keep chimpanzees.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> This is me at an early age with a baby chimpanzee.  </seg>
<seg id="8">  And I discovered there that the chimpanzees are very power hungry and wrote a book about it.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> And at that time the focus in a lot of animal research was on aggression and competition.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> I painted a whole picture of the animal kingdom, and humanity included, was that deep down we are competitors, we are aggressive, we're all out for our own profit basically.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> This is the launch of my book.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> I'm not sure how well the chimpanzees read it, but they surely seemed interested in the book.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> Now in the process of doing all this work on power and dominance and aggression and so on, I discovered that chimpanzees reconcile after fights.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> And so what you see here is two males who have had a fight.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> They ended up in a tree, and one of them holds out a hand to the other.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> And about a second after I took the picture, they came together in the fork of the tree and they kissed and embraced each other.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> Now this is very interesting because at the time everything was about competition and aggression, and so it wouldn't make any sense.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> The only thing that matters is that you win or that you lose.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> But why would you reconcile after a fight?  </seg>
<seg id="20"> That doesn't make any sense.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> This is the way bonobos do it. Bonobos do everything with sex.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> And so they also reconcile with sex.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> But the principle is exactly the same.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> The principle is that you have a valuable relationship that is damaged by conflict, so you need to do something about it.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> So my whole picture of the animal kingdom, and including humans also, started to change at that time.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> So we have this image in political science, economics, the humanities, philosophy for that matter, that man is a wolf to man.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> And so deep down our nature's actually nasty.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> I think it's a very unfair image for the wolf.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> The wolf is, after all, a very cooperative animal.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> And that's why many of you have a dog at home, which has all these characteristics also.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> And it's really unfair to humanity, because humanity is actually much more cooperative and empathic than given credit for.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> So I started getting interested in those issues and studying that in other animals.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> So these are the pillars of morality.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> If you ask anyone, "What is morality based on?" these are the two factors that always come out.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> One is reciprocity, and associated with it is a sense of justice and a sense of fairness.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> And the other one is empathy and compassion.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> And human morality is more than this, but if you would remove these two pillars, there would be not much remaining I think.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> And so they're absolutely essential.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> So let me give you a few examples here.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> This is a very old video from the Yerkes Primate Center where they train chimpanzees to cooperate.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> So this is already about a hundred years ago that we were doing experiments on cooperation.  </seg>
<seg id="42"> What you have here is two young chimpanzees who have a box, and the box is too heavy for one chimp to pull in.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> And of course, there's food on the box.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> Otherwise they wouldn't be pulling so hard.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> And so they're bringing in the box.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> And you can see that they're synchronized.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> You can see that they work together, they pull at the same moment.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> It's already a big advance over many other animals who wouldn't be able to do that.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> And now you're going to get a more interesting picture, because now one of the two chimps has been fed.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> So one of the two is not really interested in the task anymore.  </seg>
<seg id="51">    Now look at what happens at the very end of this.  </seg>
<seg id="52">  He takes basically everything.  </seg>
<seg id="53">  So there are two interesting parts about this.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> One is that the chimp on the right has a full understanding he needs the partner -- so a full understanding of the need for cooperation.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> The second one is that the partner is willing to work even though he's not interested in the food.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> Why would that be? Well that probably has to do with reciprocity.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> There's actually a lot of evidence in primates and other animals that they return favors.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> So he will get a return favor at some point in the future.  </seg>
<seg id="59"> And so that's how this all operates.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> We do the same task with elephants.  </seg>
<seg id="61"> Now with elephants, it's very dangerous to work with elephants.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> Another problem with elephants is that you cannot make an apparatus that is too heavy for a single elephant.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> Now you can probably make it, but it's going to be a pretty flimsy apparatus I think.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> And so what we did in that case -- we do these studies in Thailand for Josh Plotnik -- is we have an apparatus around which there is a rope, a single rope.  </seg>
<seg id="65"> And if you pull on this side of the rope, the rope disappears on the other side.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> So two elephants need to pick it up at exactly the same time and pull.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> Otherwise nothing is going to happen and the rope disappears.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> And the first tape you're going to see is two elephants who are released together arrive at the apparatus.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> The apparatus is on the left with food on it.  </seg>
<seg id="70"> And so they come together, they arrive together, they pick it up together and they pull together.  </seg>
<seg id="71"> So it's actually fairly simple for them.  </seg>
<seg id="72"> There they are.  </seg>
<seg id="73"> And so that's how they bring it in.  </seg>
<seg id="74"> But now we're going to make it more difficult.  </seg>
<seg id="75"> Because the whole purpose of this experiment is to see how well they understand cooperation.  </seg>
<seg id="76"> Do they understand that as well as the chimps, for example?  </seg>
<seg id="77"> And so what we do in the next step is we release one elephant before the other, and that elephant needs to be smart enough to stay there and wait and not pull at the rope -- because if he pulls at the rope, it disappears and the whole test is over.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> Now this elephant does something illegal that we did not teach it.  </seg>
<seg id="79"> But it shows the understanding that he has, because he puts his big foot on the rope, stands on the rope and waits there for the other, and then the other is going to do all the work for him.  </seg>
<seg id="80"> So it's what we call freeloading.  </seg>
<seg id="81">  But it shows the intelligence that the elephants have.  </seg>
<seg id="82"> They develop several of these alternative techniques that we did not approve of necessarily.  </seg>
<seg id="83"> So the other elephant is now coming and is going to pull it in.  </seg>
<seg id="84"> Now look at the other. The other doesn't forget to eat, of course.  </seg>
<seg id="85">  This was the cooperation, reciprocity part.  </seg>
<seg id="86"> Now something on empathy.  </seg>
<seg id="87"> Empathy is my main topic at the moment of research.  </seg>
<seg id="88"> And empathy has sort of two qualities.  </seg>
<seg id="89"> One is the understanding part of it. This is just a regular definition: the ability to understand and share the feelings of another.  </seg>
<seg id="90"> And the emotional part.  </seg>
<seg id="91"> And so empathy has basically two channels.  </seg>
<seg id="92"> One is the body channel.  </seg>
<seg id="93"> If you talk with a sad person, you're going to adopt a sad expression and a sad posture, and before you know it you feel sad.  </seg>
<seg id="94"> And that's sort of the body channel of emotional empathy, which many animals have.  </seg>
<seg id="95"> Your average dog has that also.  </seg>
<seg id="96"> That's actually why people keep mammals in the home and not turtles or snakes or something like that who don't have that kind of empathy.  </seg>
<seg id="97"> And then there's a cognitive channel, which is more that you can take the perspective of somebody else.  </seg>
<seg id="98"> And that's more limited.  </seg>
<seg id="99"> There's few animals -- I think elephants and apes can do that kind of thing -- but there are very few animals who can do that.  </seg>
<seg id="100"> So synchronization, which is part of that whole empathy mechanism is a very old one in the animal kingdom.  </seg>
<seg id="101"> And in humans, of course, we can study that with yawn contagion.  </seg>
<seg id="102"> Humans yawn when others yawn.  </seg>
<seg id="103"> And it's related to empathy.  </seg>
<seg id="104"> It activates the same areas in the brain.  </seg>
<seg id="105"> Also, we know that people who have a lot of yawn contagion are highly empathic.  </seg>
<seg id="106"> People who have problems with empathy, such as autistic children, they don't have yawn contagion.  </seg>
<seg id="107"> So it is connected.  </seg>
<seg id="108"> And we study that in our chimpanzees by presenting them with an animated head.  </seg>
<seg id="109"> So that's what you see on the upper-left, an animated head that yawns.  </seg>
<seg id="110"> And there's a chimpanzee watching, an actual real chimpanzee watching a computer screen on which we play these animations.  </seg>
<seg id="111">  So yawn contagion that you're probably all familiar with -- and maybe you're going to start yawning soon now -- is something that we share with other animals.  </seg>
<seg id="112"> And that's related to that whole body channel of synchronization that underlies empathy and that is universal in the mammals basically.  </seg>
<seg id="113"> Now we also study more complex expressions. This is consolation.  </seg>
<seg id="114"> This is a male chimpanzee who has lost a fight and he's screaming, and a juvenile comes over and puts an arm around him and calms him down.  </seg>
<seg id="115"> That's consolation. It's very similar to human consolation.  </seg>
<seg id="116"> And consolation behavior, it's empathy driven.  </seg>
<seg id="117"> Actually the way to study empathy in human children is to instruct a family member to act distressed, and then they see what young children do.  </seg>
<seg id="118"> And so it is related to empathy, and that's the kind of expressions we look at.  </seg>
<seg id="119"> We also recently published an experiment you may have heard about.  </seg>
<seg id="120"> It's on altruism and chimpanzees where the question is, do chimpanzees care about the welfare of somebody else?  </seg>
<seg id="121"> And for decades it had been assumed that only humans can do that, that only humans worry about the welfare of somebody else.  </seg>
<seg id="122"> Now we did a very simple experiment.  </seg>
<seg id="123"> We do that on chimpanzees that live in Lawrenceville, in the field station of Yerkes.  </seg>
<seg id="124"> And so that's how they live.  </seg>
<seg id="125"> And we call them into a room and do experiments with them.  </seg>
<seg id="126"> In this case, we put two chimpanzees side-by-side.  </seg>
<seg id="127"> and one has a bucket full of tokens, and the tokens have different meanings.  </seg>
<seg id="128"> One kind of token feeds only the partner who chooses, the other one feeds both of them.  </seg>
<seg id="129"> So this is a study we did with Vicky Horner.  </seg>
<seg id="130"> And here you have the two color tokens.  </seg>
<seg id="131"> So they have a whole bucket full of them.  </seg>
<seg id="132"> And they have to pick one of the two colors.  </seg>
<seg id="133"> You will see how that goes.  </seg>
<seg id="134"> So if this chimp makes the selfish choice, which is the red token in this case, he needs to give it to us.  </seg>
<seg id="135"> So we pick it up, we put it on a table where there's two food rewards, but in this case only the one on the right gets food.  </seg>
<seg id="136"> The one on the left walks away because she knows already. that this is not a good test for her.  </seg>
<seg id="137"> Then the next one is the pro-social token.  </seg>
<seg id="138"> So the one who makes the choices -- that's the interesting part here -- for the one who makes the choices, it doesn't really matter.  </seg>
<seg id="139"> So she gives us now a pro-social token and both chimps get fed.  </seg>
<seg id="140"> So the one who makes the choices always gets a reward.  </seg>
<seg id="141"> So it doesn't matter whatsoever.  </seg>
<seg id="142"> And she should actually be choosing blindly.  </seg>
<seg id="143"> But what we find is that they prefer the pro-social token.  </seg>
<seg id="144"> So this is the 50 percent line that's the random expectation.  </seg>
<seg id="145"> And especially if the partner draws attention to itself, they choose more.  </seg>
<seg id="146"> And if the partner puts pressure on them -- so if the partner starts spitting water and intimidating them -- then the choices go down.  </seg>
<seg id="147"> It's as if they're saying, "If you're not behaving, I'm not going to be pro-social today." And this is what happens without a partner, when there's no partner sitting there.  </seg>
<seg id="148"> And so we found that the chimpanzees do care about the well-being of somebody else -- especially, these are other members of their own group.  </seg>
<seg id="149"> So the final experiment that I want to mention to you is our fairness study.  </seg>
<seg id="150"> And so this became a very famous study.  </seg>
<seg id="151"> And there's now many more, because after we did this about 10 years ago, it became very well known.  </seg>
<seg id="152"> And we did that originally with capuchin monkeys.  </seg>
<seg id="153"> And I'm going to show you the first experiment that we did.  </seg>
<seg id="154"> It has now been done with dogs and with birds and with chimpanzees.  </seg>
<seg id="155"> But with Sarah Brosnan we started out with capuchin monkeys.  </seg>
<seg id="156"> So what we did is we put two capuchin monkeys side-by-side.  </seg>
<seg id="157"> Again, these animals, they live in a group, they know each other.  </seg>
<seg id="158"> We take them out of the group, put them in a test chamber.  </seg>
<seg id="159"> And there's a very simple task that they need to do.  </seg>
<seg id="160"> And if you give both of them cucumber for the task, the two monkeys side-by-side, they're perfectly willing to do this 25 times in a row.  </seg>
<seg id="161"> So cucumber, even though it's only really water in my opinion, but cucumber is perfectly fine for them.  </seg>
<seg id="162"> Now if you give the partner grapes -- the food preferences of my capuchin monkeys correspond exactly with the prices in the supermarket -- and so if you give them grapes -- it's a far better food -- then you create inequity between them.  </seg>
<seg id="163"> So that's the experiment we did.  </seg>
<seg id="164"> Recently we videotaped it with new monkeys who'd never done the task, thinking that maybe they would have a stronger reaction, and that turned out to be right.  </seg>
<seg id="165"> The one on the left is the monkey who gets cucumber.  </seg>
<seg id="166"> The one on the right is the one who gets grapes.  </seg>
<seg id="167"> The one who gets cucumber, note that the first piece of cucumber is perfectly fine.  </seg>
<seg id="168"> The first piece she eats.  </seg>
<seg id="169"> Then she sees the other one getting grape, and you will see what happens.  </seg>
<seg id="170"> So she gives a rock to us. That's the task.  </seg>
<seg id="171"> And we give her a piece of cucumber and she eats it.  </seg>
<seg id="172"> The other one needs to give a rock to us.  </seg>
<seg id="173"> And that's what she does.  </seg>
<seg id="174"> And she gets a grape and she eats it.  </seg>
<seg id="175"> The other one sees that.  </seg>
<seg id="176"> She gives a rock to us now, gets, again, cucumber.  </seg>
<seg id="177">  She tests a rock now against the wall.  </seg>
<seg id="178"> She needs to give it to us.  </seg>
<seg id="179"> And she gets cucumber again.  </seg>
<seg id="180">  So this is basically the Wall Street protest that you see here.  </seg>
<seg id="181">   Let me tell you -- I still have two minutes left, let me tell you a funny story about this.  </seg>
<seg id="182"> This study became very famous and we got a lot of comments, especially anthropologists, economists, philosophers.  </seg>
<seg id="183"> They didn't like this at all.  </seg>
<seg id="184"> Because they had decided in their minds, I believe, that fairness is a very complex issue and that animals cannot have it.  </seg>
<seg id="185"> And so one philosopher even wrote us that it was impossible that monkeys had a sense of fairness because fairness was invented during the French Revolution.  </seg>
<seg id="186">  Now another one wrote a whole chapter saying that he would believe it had something to do with fairness if the one who got grapes would refuse the grapes.  </seg>
<seg id="187"> Now the funny thing is that Sarah Brosnan, who's been doing this with chimpanzees, had a couple of combinations of chimpanzees where, indeed, the one who would get the grape would refuse the grape until the other guy also got a grape.  </seg>
<seg id="188"> So we're getting very close to the human sense of fairness.  </seg>
<seg id="189"> And I think philosophers need to rethink their philosophy for awhile.  </seg>
<seg id="190"> So let me summarize.  </seg>
<seg id="191"> I believe there's an evolved morality.  </seg>
<seg id="192"> I think morality is much more than what I've been talking about, but it would be impossible without these ingredients that we find in other primates, which are empathy and consolation, pro-social tendencies and reciprocity and a sense of fairness.  </seg>
<seg id="193"> And so we work on these particular issues to see if we can create a morality from the bottom up, so to speak, without necessarily God and religion involved, and to see how we can get to an evolved morality.  </seg>
<seg id="194"> And I thank you for your attention.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1419" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/tal_golesworthy_how_i_repaired_my_own_heart.html</url> 
<description>Tal Golesworthy is a boiler engineer -- he knows piping and plumbing. When he needed surgery to repair a life-threatening problem with his aorta, he mixed his engineering skills with his doctors' medical knowledge to design a better repair job.</description> 
<keywords>engineering,health,innovation,medicine,science,technology</keywords> 
<talkid>1419</talkid> 
<title>Tal Golesworthy: How I repaired my own heart</title> 
<seg id="1"> I'm a process engineer.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> I know all about boilers and incinerators and fabric filters and cyclones and things like that, but I also have Marfan syndrome.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> This is an inherited disorder.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> And in 1992 I participated in a genetic study and found to my horror, as you can see from the slide, that my ascending aorta was not in the normal range, the green line at the bottom.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> Everyone in here will be between 3.2 and 3.6 cm.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> I was already up at 4.4.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> And as you can see, my aorta dilated progressively, and I got closer and closer to the point where surgery was going to be necessary.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> The surgery on offer was pretty gruesome -- anesthetize you, open your chest, put you on an artificial heart and lung machine, drop your body temperature to about 18 centigrade, stop your heart, cut the aorta out, replace it with a plastic valve and a plastic aorta, and, most importantly, commit you to a lifetime of anticoagulation therapy, normally warfarin.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> The thought of the surgery was not attractive.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> The thought of the warfarin was really quite frightening.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> So I said to myself, I'm an engineer, I'm in R and D, this is just a plumbing problem.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> I can do this. I can change this.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> So I set out to change the entire treatment for aortic dilation.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> The project aim is really quite simple.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> The only real problem with the ascending aorta in people with Marfan syndrome is it lacks some tensile strength.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> So the possibility exists to simply externally wrap the pipe.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> And it would remain stable and operate quite happily.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> If your high-pressure hose pipe, or your high-pressure hydraulic line, bulges a little, you just wrap some tape around the outside of it.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> It really is that simple in concept, though not in execution.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> The great advantage of an external support for me was that I could retain all of my own bits, all of my own endothelium and valves, and not need any anticoagulation therapy.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> So where do we start?  </seg>
<seg id="22"> Well this is a sagittal slice through me.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> You could see in the middle that device, that little structure, squeezing out.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> Now that's a left ventricle pushing blood up through the aortic valve -- you can see two of the leaflets of the aortic valve working there -- up into the ascending aorta.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> And it's that part, the ascending aorta, which dilates and ultimately bursts, which, of course, is fatal.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> We started by organizing image acquisition from magnetic resonance imaging machines and CT imaging machines from which to make a model of the patient's aorta.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> This is a model of my aorta.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> I've got a real one in my pocket, if anyone would like to look at it and play with it.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> You can see, it's quite a complex structure.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> It has a funny trilobal shape at the bottom, which contains the aortic valve.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> It then comes back into a round form and then tapers and curves off.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> So it's quite a difficult structure to produce.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> This, like I say, is a CAD model of me, and this is one of the later CAD models.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> We went through an iterative process of producing better and better models.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> When we produced that model we turn it into a solid plastic model, as you can see,  </seg>
<seg id="36"> using a rapid prototyping technique, another engineering technique.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> We then use that former to manufacture a perfectly bespoke porous textile mesh, which takes the shape of the former and perfectly fits the aorta.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> So this is absolutely personalized medicine at its best really.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> Every patient we do has an absolutely bespoke implant.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> Once you've made it, the installation's quite easy.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> John Pepper, bless his heart, professor of cardiothoracic surgery -- never done it before in his life -- he put the first one in, didn't like it, took it out, put the second one in.  </seg>
<seg id="42"> Happy, away I went.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> Four and a half hours on the table and everything was done.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> So the surgical implantation actually was the easiest part.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> If you compare our new treatment to the existing alternative, the so-called composite aortic root graft, there are one of two startling comparisons, which I'm sure will be clear to all of you.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> Two hours to install one of our devices compared to six hours for the existing treatment.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> The existing treatment requires, as I've said, the heart and lung bypass machine and it requires a total body cooling.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> We don't need any of that; we work on a beating heart.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> He opens you up, he accesses the aorta while your heart is beating, all at the right temperature.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> No breaking into your circulatory system.  </seg>
<seg id="51"> So it really is great.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> But for me, absolutely the best point is there is no anticoagulation therapy required.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> I don't take any drugs at all other than recreational ones that I would choose to take.  </seg>
<seg id="54">  And in fact, if you speak to people who are on long-term warfarin, it is a serious compromise to your quality of life.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> And even worse, it inevitably foreshortens your life.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> Likewise, if you have the artificial valve option, you're committed to antibiotic therapy whenever you have any intrusive medical treatment at all.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> Even trips to the dentist require that you take antibiotics, in case you get an internal infection on the valve.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> Again, I don't have any of that, so I'm entirely free.  </seg>
<seg id="59"> My aorta is fixed, I haven't got to worry about it, which is a rebirth for me.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> Back to the theme of the presentation: In multidisciplinary research, how on earth does a process engineer used to working with boilers end up producing a medical device which transforms his own life?  </seg>
<seg id="61"> Well the answer to that is a multidisciplinary team.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> This is a list of the core team.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> And as you can see, there are not only two principal technical disciplines there, medicine and engineering, but also there are various specialists from within those two disciplines.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> John Pepper there was the cardiac surgeon who did the actual work on me, but everyone else there had to contribute one way or another.  </seg>
<seg id="65"> Raad Mohiaddin, medical radiologist: We had to get good quality images from which to make the CAD model.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> Warren Thornton, who still does all our CAD models for us, had to write a bespoke piece of CAD code to produce this model from this really rather difficult input data set.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> There are some barriers to this though. There are some problems with it.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> Jargon is a big one.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> I would think no one in this room understands those four first jargon points there.  </seg>
<seg id="70"> The engineers amongst you will recognize rapid prototyping and CAD.  </seg>
<seg id="71"> The medics amongst you, if there are any, will recognize the first two.  </seg>
<seg id="72"> But there will be nobody else in this room that understands all of those four words.  </seg>
<seg id="73"> Taking the jargon out was very important to ensure that everyone in the team understood exactly what was meant when a particular phrase was used.  </seg>
<seg id="74"> Our disciplinary conventions were funny as well.  </seg>
<seg id="75"> We took a lot of horizontal slice images through me, produced those slices and then used those to build a CAD model.  </seg>
<seg id="76"> And the very first CAD model we made, the surgeons were playing with the plastic model, couldn't quite figure it out.  </seg>
<seg id="77"> And then we realized that it was actually a mirror image of the real aorta.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> And it was a mirror image because in the real world we always look down on plans, plans of houses or streets or maps.  </seg>
<seg id="79"> In the medical world they look up at plans.  </seg>
<seg id="80"> So the horizontal images were all an inversion.  </seg>
<seg id="81"> So one needs to be careful with disciplinary conventions.  </seg>
<seg id="82"> Everyone needs to understand what is assumed and what is not assumed.  </seg>
<seg id="83"> Institutional barriers were another serious headache in the project.  </seg>
<seg id="84"> The Brompton Hospital was taken over by Imperial College's School of Medicine, and there are some seriously bad relationship problems between the two organizations.  </seg>
<seg id="85"> I was working with Imperial and the Brompton, and this generated some serious problems with the project, really problems that shouldn't exist.  </seg>
<seg id="86"> Research and ethics committee: If you want to do anything new in surgery, you have to get a license from your local research and ethics.  </seg>
<seg id="87"> I'm sure it's the same in Poland.  </seg>
<seg id="88"> There will be some form of equivalent, which licenses new types of surgery.  </seg>
<seg id="89"> We didn't only have the bureaucratic problems associated with that, was also had professional jealousies.  </seg>
<seg id="90"> There were people on the research and ethics committee who really didn't want to see John Pepper succeed again, because he's so successful.  </seg>
<seg id="91"> And they made extra problems for us.  </seg>
<seg id="92"> Bureaucratic problems: Ultimately when you have a new treatment you have to have a guidance note going out for all of the hospitals in the country.  </seg>
<seg id="93"> In the U.K. we have the National Institute for Clinical Excellence, NICE.  </seg>
<seg id="94"> You'll have an equivalent in Poland, no doubt.  </seg>
<seg id="95"> We had to get past the NICE problem.  </seg>
<seg id="96"> We now have a great clinical guidance out on the Net.  </seg>
<seg id="97"> So any of the hospitals interested can come along, read the NICE report get in touch with us and then get doing it themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="98"> Funding barriers: Another big area to be concerned with. A big problem with understanding one of those perspectives: When we first approached one of the big U.K. charitable organizations that funds this kind of stuff, what they were looking at was essentially an engineering proposal.  </seg>
<seg id="99"> They didn't understand it; they were doctors, they were next to God.  </seg>
<seg id="100"> It must be rubbish. They binned it.  </seg>
<seg id="101"> So in the end I went to private investors and I just gave up on it.  </seg>
<seg id="102"> But most R and D is going to be institutionally funded, by the Polish Academy of Sciences or the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council or whatever, and you need to get past those people.  </seg>
<seg id="103"> Jargon is a huge problem when you're trying to work across disciplines, because in an engineering world, we all understand CAD and R.P. -- not in the medical world.  </seg>
<seg id="104"> I suppose ultimately the funding bureaucrats have really got to get their act together.  </seg>
<seg id="105"> They've really got to start talking to each other, and they've got to exercise a bit of imagination, if that's not too much to ask -- which it probably is.  </seg>
<seg id="106"> I've coined a phrase "obstructive conservatism."  </seg>
<seg id="107"> So many people in the medical world don't want to change, particularly not when some jumped-up engineer has come along with the answer.  </seg>
<seg id="108"> They don't want to change.  </seg>
<seg id="109"> They simply want to do whatever they've done before.  </seg>
<seg id="110"> And in fact, there are many surgeons in the U.K. still waiting for one of our patients to have some sort of episode, so that they can say, "Ah, I told you that was no good." We've actually got 30 patients.  </seg>
<seg id="111"> I'm at seven and a half years.  </seg>
<seg id="112"> We've got 90 post-op patient years between us, and we haven't had a single problem.  </seg>
<seg id="113"> And still, there are people in the U.K. saying, "Yeah, that external aortic root, yeah, it'll never work, you know." It really is a problem. It really is a problem.  </seg>
<seg id="114"> I'm sure everyone in this room has come across arrogance amongst medics, doctors, surgeons at some point.  </seg>
<seg id="115"> The middle point is simply the way that the doctors protect themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="116"> "Yeah, well of course, I'm looking after my patient."  </seg>
<seg id="117"> I think it's not good, but there you are, that's my view.  </seg>
<seg id="118"> Egos, of course, again, a huge problem If you're working in a multidisciplinary team, you've got to give your guys the benefit of the doubt.  </seg>
<seg id="119"> You've got to express support for them.  </seg>
<seg id="120"> Tom Treasure, professor of cardiothoracic surgery: incredible guy.  </seg>
<seg id="121"> Dead easy to give him respect.  </seg>
<seg id="122"> Him giving me respect? Slightly different.  </seg>
<seg id="123"> That's all the bad news.  </seg>
<seg id="124"> The good news is the benefits are stonkingly huge.  </seg>
<seg id="125"> Translate that one. I bet they can't.  </seg>
<seg id="126">  When you have a group of people who have had a different professional training, a different professional experience, they not only have a different knowledge base, but they have a different perspective on everything.  </seg>
<seg id="127"> And if you can bring those guys together and you can get them talking and understanding each other, the results can be spectacular.  </seg>
<seg id="128"> You can find novel solutions, really novel solutions, that have never been looked at before very, very quickly and easily.  </seg>
<seg id="129"> You can shortcut huge amounts of work simply by using the extended knowledge base you have.  </seg>
<seg id="130"> And as a result, it's an entirely different use of the technology and the knowledge around you.  </seg>
<seg id="131"> The result of all this is that you can get incredibly quick progress on incredibly small budgets.  </seg>
<seg id="132"> I'm so embarrassed at how cheap it was to get from my idea to me being implanted that I'm not prepared to tell you what it cost.  </seg>
<seg id="133"> Because I suspect there are absolutely standard surgical treatments probably in the USA which cost more for a one-off patient than the cost of us getting from my dream to my reality.  </seg>
<seg id="134"> That's all I want to say, and I've got three minutes left.  </seg>
<seg id="135"> So Heather's going to like me.  </seg>
<seg id="136"> If you have any questions, please come up and talk to me later on.  </seg>
<seg id="137"> It would be a pleasure to speak with you. Many thanks.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1409" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/sherry_turkle_alone_together.html</url> 
<description>As we expect more from technology, do we expect less from each other? Sherry Turkle studies how our devices and online personas are redefining human connection and communication -- and asks us to think deeply about the new kinds of connection we want to have.</description> 
<keywords>communication,community,culture,technology</keywords> 
<talkid>1409</talkid> 
<title>Sherry Turkle: Connected, but alone?</title> 
<seg id="1"> Just a moment ago, my daughter Rebecca texted me for good luck.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> Her text said, "Mom, you will rock." I love this.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> Getting that text was like getting a hug.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> I embody the central paradox.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> I'm a woman who loves getting texts who's going to tell you that too many of them can be a problem.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> Actually that reminder of my daughter brings me to the beginning of my story.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> 1996, when I gave my first TEDTalk, Rebecca was five years old and she was sitting right there in the front row.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> I had just written a book that celebrated our life on the internet and I was about to be on the cover of Wired magazine.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> In those heady days, we were experimenting with chat rooms and online virtual communities.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> We were exploring different aspects of ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> And then we unplugged.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> I was excited.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> And, as a psychologist, what excited me most was the idea that we would use what we learned in the virtual world about ourselves, about our identity, to live better lives in the real world.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> Now fast-forward to 2012.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> I'm back here on the TED stage again.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> My daughter's 20. She's a college student.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> She sleeps with her cellphone, so do I.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> And I've just written a new book, but this time it's not one that will get me on the cover of Wired magazine.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> So what happened?  </seg>
<seg id="20"> I'm still excited by technology, but I believe, and I'm here to make the case, that we're letting it take us places that we don't want to go.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> Over the past 15 years, I've studied technologies of mobile communication and I've interviewed hundreds and hundreds of people, young and old, about their plugged in lives.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> And what I've found is that our little devices, those little devices in our pockets, are so psychologically powerful that they don't only change what we do, they change who we are.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> Some of the things we do now with our devices are things that, only a few years ago, we would have found odd or disturbing, but they've quickly come to seem familiar, just how we do things.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> So just to take some quick examples: People text or do email during corporate board meetings.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> They text and shop and go on Facebook during classes, during presentations, actually during all meetings.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> People talk to me about the important new skill of making eye contact while you're texting.  </seg>
<seg id="27">  People explain to me that it's hard, but that it can be done.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> Parents text and do email at breakfast and at dinner while their children complain about not having their parents' full attention.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> But then these same children deny each other their full attention.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> This is a recent shot of my daughter and her friends being together while not being together.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> And we even text at funerals.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> I study this.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> We remove ourselves from our grief or from our revery and we go into our phones.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> Why does this matter?  </seg>
<seg id="35"> It matters to me because I think we're setting ourselves up for trouble -- trouble certainly in how we relate to each other, but also trouble in how we relate to ourselves and our capacity for self-reflection.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> We're getting used to a new way of being alone together.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> People want to be with each other, but also elsewhere -- connected to all the different places they want to be.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> People want to customize their lives.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> They want to go in and out of all the places they are because the thing that matters most to them is control over where they put their attention.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> So you want to go to that board meeting, but you only want to pay attention to the bits that interest you.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> And some people think that's a good thing.  </seg>
<seg id="42"> But you can end up hiding from each other, even as we're all constantly connected to each other.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> A 50-year-old business man lamented to me that he feels he doesn't have colleagues anymore at work.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> When he goes to work, he doesn't stop by to talk to anybody, he doesn't call.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> And he says he doesn't want to interrupt his colleagues because, he says, "They're too busy on their email." But then he stops himself and he says, "You know, I'm not telling you the truth.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> I'm the one who doesn't want to be interrupted.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> I think I should want to, but actually I'd rather just do things on my Blackberry." Across the generations, I see that people can't get enough of each other, if and only if they can have each other at a distance, in amounts they can control.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> I call it the Goldilocks effect: not too close, not too far, just right.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> But what might feel just right for that middle-aged executive can be a problem for an adolescent who needs to develop face-to-face relationships.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> An 18-year-old boy who uses texting for almost everything says to me wistfully, "Someday, someday, but certainly not now, I'd like to learn how to have a conversation." When I ask people "What's wrong with having a conversation?" People say, "I'll tell you what's wrong with having a conversation.  </seg>
<seg id="51"> It takes place in real time and you can't control what you're going to say." So that's the bottom line.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> Texting, email, posting, all of these things let us present the self as we want to be.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> We get to edit, and that means we get to delete, and that means we get to retouch, the face, the voice, the flesh, the body -- not too little, not too much, just right.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> Human relationships are rich and they're messy and they're demanding.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> And we clean them up with technology.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> And when we do, one of the things that can happen is that we sacrifice conversation for mere connection.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> We short-change ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> And over time, we seem to forget this, or we seem to stop caring.  </seg>
<seg id="59"> I was caught off guard when Stephen Colbert asked me a profound question, a profound question.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> He said, "Don't all those little tweets, don't all those little sips of online communication, add up to one big gulp of real conversation?" My answer was no, they don't add up.  </seg>
<seg id="61"> Connecting in sips may work for gathering discreet bits of information, they may work for saying, "I'm thinking about you," or even for saying, "I love you," -- I mean, look at how I felt when I got that text from my daughter -- but they don't really work for learning about each other, for really coming to know and understand each other.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> And we use conversations with each other to learn how to have conversations with ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> So a flight from conversation can really matter because it can compromise our capacity for self-reflection.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> For kids growing up, that skill is the bedrock of development.  </seg>
<seg id="65"> Over and over I hear, "I would rather text than talk." And what I'm seeing is that people get so used to being short-changed out of real conversation, so used to getting by with less, that they've become almost willing to dispense with people altogether.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> So for example, many people share with me this wish, that some day a more advanced version of Siri, the digital assistant on Apple's iPhone, will be more like a best friend, someone who will listen when others won't.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> I believe this wish reflects a painful truth that I've learned in the past 15 years.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> That feeling that no one is listening to me is very important in our relationships with technology.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> That's why it's so appealing to have a Facebook page or a Twitter feed -- so many automatic listeners. And the feeling that no one is listening to me make us want to spend time with machines that seem to care about us.  </seg>
<seg id="70"> We're developing robots, they call them sociable robots, that are specifically designed to be companions -- to the elderly, to our children, to us.  </seg>
<seg id="71"> Have we so lost confidence that we will be there for each other?  </seg>
<seg id="72"> During my research I worked in nursing homes, and I brought in these sociable robots that were designed to give the elderly the feeling that they were understood.  </seg>
<seg id="73"> And one day I came in and a woman who had lost a child was talking to a robot in the shape of a baby seal.  </seg>
<seg id="74"> It seemed to be looking in her eyes.  </seg>
<seg id="75"> It seemed to be following the conversation.  </seg>
<seg id="76"> It comforted her.  </seg>
<seg id="77"> And many people found this amazing.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> But that woman was trying to make sense of her life with a machine that had no experience of the arc of a human life.  </seg>
<seg id="79"> That robot put on a great show.  </seg>
<seg id="80"> And we're vulnerable.  </seg>
<seg id="81"> People experience pretend empathy as though it were the real thing.  </seg>
<seg id="82"> So during that moment when that woman was experiencing that pretend empathy, I was thinking, "That robot can't empathize.  </seg>
<seg id="83"> It doesn't face death.  </seg>
<seg id="84"> It doesn't know life." And as that woman took comfort in her robot companion, I didn't find it amazing; I found it one of the most wrenching, complicated moments in my 15 years of work.  </seg>
<seg id="85"> But when I stepped back, I felt myself at the cold, hard center of a perfect storm.  </seg>
<seg id="86"> We expect more from technology and less from each other.  </seg>
<seg id="87"> And I ask myself, "Why have things come to this?" And I believe it's because technology appeals to us most where we are most vulnerable.  </seg>
<seg id="88"> And we are vulnerable.  </seg>
<seg id="89"> We're lonely, but we're afraid of intimacy.  </seg>
<seg id="90"> And so from social networks to sociable robots, we're designing technologies that will give us the illusion of companionship without the demands of friendship.  </seg>
<seg id="91"> We turn to technology to help us feel connected in ways we can comfortably control.  </seg>
<seg id="92"> But we're not so comfortable.  </seg>
<seg id="93"> We are not so much in control.  </seg>
<seg id="94"> These days, those phones in our pockets are changing our minds and hearts because they offer us three gratifying fantasies.  </seg>
<seg id="95"> One, that we can put our attention wherever we want it to be; two, that we will always be heard; and three, that we will never have to be alone.  </seg>
<seg id="96"> And that third idea, that we will never have to be alone, is central to changing our psyches.  </seg>
<seg id="97"> Because the moment that people are alone, even for a few seconds, they become anxious, they panic, they fidget, they reach for a device.  </seg>
<seg id="98"> Just think of people at a checkout line or at a red light.  </seg>
<seg id="99"> Being alone feels like a problem that needs to be solved.  </seg>
<seg id="100"> And so people try to solve it by connecting.  </seg>
<seg id="101"> But here, connection is more like a symptom than a cure.  </seg>
<seg id="102"> It expresses, but it doesn't solve, an underlying problem.  </seg>
<seg id="103"> But more than a symptom, constant connection is changing the way people think of themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="104"> It's shaping a new way of being.  </seg>
<seg id="105"> The best way to describe it is, I share therefore I am.  </seg>
<seg id="106"> We use technology to define ourselves by sharing our thoughts and feelings even as we're having them.  </seg>
<seg id="107"> So before it was: I have a feeling, I want to make a call.  </seg>
<seg id="108"> Now it's: I want to have a feeling, I need to send a text.  </seg>
<seg id="109"> The problem with this new regime of "I share therefore I am" is that, if we don't have connection, we don't feel like ourselves. We almost don't feel ourselves. So what do we do? We connect more and more.  </seg>
<seg id="110"> But in the process, we set ourselves up to be isolated.  </seg>
<seg id="111"> How do you get from connection to isolation?  </seg>
<seg id="112"> You end up isolated if you don't cultivate the capacity for solitude, the ability to be separate, to gather yourself.  </seg>
<seg id="113"> Solitude is where you find yourself so that you can reach out to other people and form real attachments.  </seg>
<seg id="114"> When we don't have the capacity for solitude, we turn to other people in order to feel less anxious or in order to feel alive.  </seg>
<seg id="115"> When this happens, we're not able to appreciate who they are.  </seg>
<seg id="116"> It's as though we're using them as spare parts to support our fragile sense of self.  </seg>
<seg id="117"> We slip into thinking that always being connected is going to make us fell less alone.  </seg>
<seg id="118"> But we're at risk, because actually it's the opposite that's true.  </seg>
<seg id="119"> If we're not able to be alone, we're going to be more lonely.  </seg>
<seg id="120"> And if we don't teach our children to be alone, they're only going to know When I spoke at TED in 1996, reporting on my studies of the early virtual communities, I said, "Those who make the most of their lives on the screen come to it in a spirit of self-reflection." And that's what I'm calling for here, now: reflection and, more than that, a conversation about where our current use of technology may be taking us, what it might be costing us.  </seg>
<seg id="121"> We're smitten with technology.  </seg>
<seg id="122"> And we're afraid, like young lovers, that too much talking might spoil the romance.  </seg>
<seg id="123"> But it's time to talk.  </seg>
<seg id="124"> We grew up with digital technology and so we see it as all grown up.  </seg>
<seg id="125"> But it's not, it's early days.  </seg>
<seg id="126"> There's plenty of time for us to reconsider how we use it, how we build it.  </seg>
<seg id="127"> I'm not suggesting that we turn away from our devices, just that we develop a more self-aware relationship with them, with each other and with ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="128"> I see some first steps.  </seg>
<seg id="129"> Start thinking of solitude as a good thing.  </seg>
<seg id="130"> Make room for it.  </seg>
<seg id="131"> Find ways to demonstrate this as a value to your children.  </seg>
<seg id="132"> Create sacred spaces at home -- the kitchen, the dining room -- and reclaim them for conversation.  </seg>
<seg id="133"> Do the same thing at work.  </seg>
<seg id="134"> At work, we're so busy communicating that we often don't have time to think, we don't have time to talk, about the things that really matter.  </seg>
<seg id="135"> Change that.  </seg>
<seg id="136"> Most important, we all really need to listen to each other, including to the boring bits.  </seg>
<seg id="137"> Because it's when we stumble or hesitate or lose our words that we reveal ourselves to each other.  </seg>
<seg id="138"> Technology is making a bid to redefine human connection -- how we care for each other, how we care for ourselves -- but it's also giving us the opportunity to affirm our values and our direction.  </seg>
<seg id="139"> I'm optimistic.  </seg>
<seg id="140"> We have everything we need to start.  </seg>
<seg id="141"> We have each other.  </seg>
<seg id="142"> And we have the greatest chance of success if we recognize our vulnerability.  </seg>
<seg id="143"> That we listen when technology says it will take something complicated and promises something simpler.  </seg>
<seg id="144"> So in my work, I hear that life is hard, relationships are filled with risk.  </seg>
<seg id="145"> And then there's technology -- simpler, hopeful, optimistic, ever-young.  </seg>
<seg id="146"> It's like calling in the cavalry.  </seg>
<seg id="147"> An ad campaign promises that online and with avatars, you can "Finally, love your friends love your body, love your life, online and with avatars." We're drawn to virtual romance, to computer games that seem like worlds, to the idea that robots, robots, will someday be our true companions.  </seg>
<seg id="148"> We spend an evening on the social network instead of going to the pub with friends.  </seg>
<seg id="149"> But our fantasies of substitution have cost us.  </seg>
<seg id="150"> Now we all need to focus on the many, many ways technology can lead us back to our real lives, our own bodies, our own communities, our own politics, our own planet.  </seg>
<seg id="151"> They need us.  </seg>
<seg id="152"> Let's talk about how we can use digital technology, the technology of our dreams, to make this life the life we can love.  </seg>
<seg id="153"> Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1421" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/atul_gawande_how_do_we_heal_medicine.html</url> 
<description>Our medical systems are broken. Doctors are capable of extraordinary  treatments, but they are losing their core focus: actually treating people. Doctor and writer Atul Gawande suggests we take a step back and look at new ways to do medicine -- with fewer cowboys and more pit crews.</description> 
<keywords>health care,medicine</keywords> 
<talkid>1421</talkid> 
<title>Atul Gawande: How do we heal medicine?</title> 
<seg id="1"> I got my start in writing and research as a surgical trainee, as someone who was a long ways away from becoming any kind of an expert at anything.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> So the natural question you ask then at that point is, how do I get good at what I'm trying to do?  </seg>
<seg id="3"> And it became a question of, how do we all get good at what we're trying to do?  </seg>
<seg id="4"> It's hard enough to learn to get the skills, try to learn all the material you have to absorb at any task you're taking on.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> I had to think about how I sew and how I cut, but then also how I pick the right person to come to an operating room.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> And then in the midst of all this came this new context for thinking about what it meant to be good.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> In the last few years we realized we were in the deepest crisis of medicine's existence due to something you don't normally think about when you're a doctor concerned with how you do good for people, which is the cost of health care.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> There's not a country in the world that now is not asking whether we can afford what doctors do.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> The political fight that we've developed has become one around whether it's the government that's the problem or is it insurance companies that are the problem.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> And the answer is yes and no; it's deeper than all of that.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> The cause of our troubles is actually the complexity that science has given us.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> And in order to understand this, I'm going to take you back a couple of generations.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> I want to take you back to a time when Lewis Thomas was writing in his book, "The Youngest Science."  </seg>
<seg id="14"> Lewis Thomas was a physician-writer, one of my favorite writers.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> And he wrote this book to explain, among other things, what it was like to be a medical intern at the Boston City Hospital in the pre-penicillin year of 1937.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> It was a time when medicine was cheap and very ineffective.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> If you were in a hospital, he said, it was going to do you good only because it offered you some warmth, some food, shelter, and maybe the caring attention of a nurse.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> Doctors and medicine made no difference at all.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> That didn't seem to prevent the doctors from being frantically busy in their days, as he explained.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> What they were trying to do was figure out whether you might have one of the diagnoses for which they could do something.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> And there were a few.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> You might have a lobar pneumonia, for example, and they could give you an antiserum, an injection of rabid antibodies to the bacterium streptococcus, if the intern sub-typed it correctly.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> If you had an acute congestive heart failure, they could bleed a pint of blood from you by opening up an arm vein, giving you a crude leaf preparation of digitalis and then giving you oxygen by tent.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> If you had early signs of paralysis and you were really good at asking personal questions, you might figure out that this paralysis someone has is from syphilis, in which case you could give this nice concoction of mercury and arsenic -- as long as you didn't overdose them and kill them.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> Beyond these sorts of things, a medical doctor didn't have a lot that they could do.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> This was when the core structure of medicine was created -- what it meant to be good at what we did and how we wanted to build medicine to be.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> It was at a time when what was known you could know, you could hold it all in your head, and you could do it all.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> If you had a prescription pad, if you had a nurse, if you had a hospital that would give you a place to convalesce, maybe some basic tools, you really could do it all.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> You set the fracture, you drew the blood, you spun the blood, looked at it under the microscope, you plated the culture, you injected the antiserum.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> This was a life as a craftsman.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> As a result, we built it around a culture and set of values that said what you were good at was being daring, at being courageous, at being independent and self-sufficient.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> Autonomy was our highest value.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> Go a couple generations forward to where we are, though, and it looks like a completely different world.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> We have now found treatments for nearly all of the tens of thousands of conditions that a human being can have.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> We can't cure it all.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> We can't guarantee that everybody will live a long and healthy life.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> But we can make it possible for most.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> But what does it take?  </seg>
<seg id="39"> Well, we've now discovered 4,000 medical and surgical procedures.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> We've discovered 6,000 drugs that I'm now licensed to prescribe.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> And we're trying to deploy this capability, town by town, to every person alive -- in our own country, let alone around the world.  </seg>
<seg id="42"> And we've reached the point where we've realized, as doctors, we can't know it all.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> We can't do it all by ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> There was a study where they looked at how many clinicians it took to take care of you if you came into a hospital, as it changed over time.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> And in the year 1970, it took just over two full-time equivalents of clinicians.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> it took basically the nursing time and then just a little bit of time for a doctor who more or less checked in on you once a day.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> By the end of the 20th century, it had become more than 15 clinicians for the same typical hospital patient -- specialists, physical therapists, the nurses.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> We're all specialists now, even the primary care physicians.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> Everyone just has a piece of the care.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> But holding onto that structure we built around the daring, independence, self-sufficiency of each of those people has become a disaster.  </seg>
<seg id="51"> We have trained, hired and rewarded people to be cowboys.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> But it's pit crews that we need, pit crews for patients.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> There's evidence all around us: 40 percent of our coronary artery disease patients in our communities receive incomplete or inappropriate care.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> 60 percent of our asthma, stroke patients receive incomplete or inappropriate care.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> Two million people come into hospitals and pick up an infection they didn't have because someone failed to follow the basic practices of hygiene.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> Our experience as people who get sick, need help from other people, is that we have amazing clinicians that we can turn to -- hardworking, incredibly well-trained and very smart -- that we have access to incredible technologies that give us great hope, but little sense that it consistently all comes together for you from start to finish in a successful way.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> There's another sign that we need pit crews, and that's the unmanageable cost of our care.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> Now we in medicine, I think, are baffled by this question of cost.  </seg>
<seg id="59"> We want to say, "This is just the way it is.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> This is just what medicine requires." When you go from a world where you treated arthritis with aspirin, that mostly didn't do the job, to one where, if it gets bad enough, we can do a hip replacement, a knee replacement that gives you years, maybe decades, without disability, a dramatic change, well is it any surprise that that $40,000 hip replacement replacing the 10-cent aspirin is more expensive?  </seg>
<seg id="61"> It's just the way it is.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> But I think we're ignoring certain facts that tell us something about what we can do.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> As we've looked at the data about the results that have come as the complexity has increased, we found that the most expensive care is not necessarily the best care.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> And vice versa, the best care often turns out to be the least expensive -- has fewer complications, the people get more efficient at what they do.  </seg>
<seg id="65"> And what that means is there's hope.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> Because [if] to have the best results, you really needed the most expensive care in the country, or in the world, well then we really would be talking about rationing who we're going to cut off from Medicare.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> That would be really our only choice.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> But when we look at the positive deviants -- the ones who are getting the best results at the lowest costs -- we find the ones that look the most like systems are the most successful.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> That is to say, they found ways to get all of the different pieces, all of the different components, to come together into a whole.  </seg>
<seg id="70"> Having great components is not enough, and yet we've been obsessed in medicine with components.  </seg>
<seg id="71"> We want the best drugs, the best technologies, the best specialists, but we don't think too much about how it all comes together.  </seg>
<seg id="72"> It's a terrible design strategy actually.  </seg>
<seg id="73"> There's a famous thought experiment that touches exactly on this that said, what if you built a car from the very best car parts?  </seg>
<seg id="74"> Well it would lead you to put in Porsche brakes, a Ferrari engine, a Volvo body, a BMW chassis.  </seg>
<seg id="75"> And you put it all together and what do you get?  </seg>
<seg id="76"> A very expensive pile of junk that does not go anywhere.  </seg>
<seg id="77"> And that is what medicine can feel like sometimes.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> It's not a system.  </seg>
<seg id="79"> Now a system, however, when things start to come together, you realize it has certain skills for acting and looking that way.  </seg>
<seg id="80"> Skill number one is the ability to recognize success and the ability to recognize failure.  </seg>
<seg id="81"> When you are a specialist, you can't see the end result very well.  </seg>
<seg id="82"> You have to become really interested in data, unsexy as that sounds.  </seg>
<seg id="83"> One of my colleagues is a surgeon in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, and he got interested in the question of, well how many CT scans did they do for their community in Cedar Rapids?  </seg>
<seg id="84"> He got interested in this because there had been government reports, newspaper reports, journal articles saying that there had been too many CT scans done.  </seg>
<seg id="85"> He didn't see it in his own patients.  </seg>
<seg id="86"> And so he asked the question, "How many did we do?" and he wanted to get the data.  </seg>
<seg id="87"> It took him three months.  </seg>
<seg id="88"> No one had asked this question in his community before.  </seg>
<seg id="89"> And what he found was that, for the 300,000 people in their community, in the previous year they had done 52,000 CT scans.  </seg>
<seg id="90"> They had found a problem.  </seg>
<seg id="91"> Which brings us to skill number two a system has.  </seg>
<seg id="92"> Skill one, find where your failures are.  </seg>
<seg id="93"> Skill two is devise solutions.  </seg>
<seg id="94"> I got interested in this when the World Health Organization came to my team asking if we could help with a project to reduce deaths in surgery.  </seg>
<seg id="95"> The volume of surgery had spread around the world, but the safety of surgery had not.  </seg>
<seg id="96"> Now our usual tactics for tackling problems like these are to do more training, give people more specialization or bring in more technology.  </seg>
<seg id="97"> Well in surgery, you couldn't have people who are more specialized and you couldn't have people who are better trained.  </seg>
<seg id="98"> And yet we see unconscionable levels of death, disability that could be avoided.  </seg>
<seg id="99"> And so we looked at what other high-risk industries do.  </seg>
<seg id="100"> We looked at skyscraper construction, we looked at the aviation world, and we found that they have technology, they have training, and then they have one other thing: They have checklists.  </seg>
<seg id="101"> I did not expect to be spending a significant part of my time as a Harvard surgeon worrying about checklists.  </seg>
<seg id="102"> And yet, what we found were that these were tools to help make experts better.  </seg>
<seg id="103"> We got the lead safety engineer for Boeing to help us.  </seg>
<seg id="104"> Could we design a checklist for surgery?  </seg>
<seg id="105"> Not for the lowest people on the totem pole, but for the folks who were all the way around the chain, the entire team including the surgeons.  </seg>
<seg id="106"> And what they taught us was that designing a checklist to help people handle complexity actually involves more difficulty than I had understood.  </seg>
<seg id="107"> You have to think about things like pause points.  </seg>
<seg id="108"> You need to identify the moments in a process when you can actually catch a problem before it's a danger and do something about it.  </seg>
<seg id="109"> You have to identify that this is a before-takeoff checklist.  </seg>
<seg id="110"> And then you need to focus on the killer items.  </seg>
<seg id="111"> An aviation checklist, like this one for a single-engine plane, isn't a recipe for how to fly a plane, it's a reminder of the key things that get forgotten or missed if they're not checked.  </seg>
<seg id="112"> So we did this.  </seg>
<seg id="113"> We created a 19-item two-minute checklist  </seg>
<seg id="114"> for surgical teams.  </seg>
<seg id="115"> We had the pause points immediately before anesthesia is given, immediately before the knife hits the skin, immediately before the patient leaves the room.  </seg>
<seg id="116"> And we had a mix of dumb stuff on there -- making sure an antibiotic is given in the right time frame because that cuts the infection rate by half -- and then interesting stuff, because you can't make a recipe for something as complicated as surgery.  </seg>
<seg id="117"> Instead, you can make a recipe for how to have a team that's prepared for the unexpected.  </seg>
<seg id="118"> And we had items like making sure everyone in the room had introduced themselves by name at the start of the day, because you get half a dozen people or more who are sometimes coming together as a team for the very first time that day that you're coming in.  </seg>
<seg id="119"> We implemented this checklist in eight hospitals around the world, deliberately in places from rural Tanzania to the University of Washington in Seattle.  </seg>
<seg id="120"> We found that after they adopted it the complication rates fell 35 percent.  </seg>
<seg id="121"> It fell in every hospital it went into.  </seg>
<seg id="122"> The death rates fell 47 percent.  </seg>
<seg id="123"> This was bigger than a drug.  </seg>
<seg id="124">  And that brings us to skill number three, the ability to implement this, to get colleagues across the entire chain to actually do these things.  </seg>
<seg id="125"> And it's been slow to spread.  </seg>
<seg id="126"> This is not yet our norm in surgery -- let alone making checklists to go onto childbirth and other areas.  </seg>
<seg id="127"> There's a deep resistance because using these tools forces us to confront that we're not a system, forces us to behave with a different set of values.  </seg>
<seg id="128"> Just using a checklist requires you to embrace different values from the ones we've had, like humility, discipline, teamwork.  </seg>
<seg id="129"> This is the opposite of what we were built on: independence, self-sufficiency, autonomy.  </seg>
<seg id="130"> I met an actual cowboy, by the way.  </seg>
<seg id="131"> I asked him, what was it like to actually herd a thousand cattle across hundreds of miles?  </seg>
<seg id="132"> How did you do that?  </seg>
<seg id="133"> And he said, "We have the cowboys stationed at distinct places all around." They communicate electronically constantly, and they have protocols and checklists for how they handle everything --  -- from bad weather to emergencies or inoculations for the cattle.  </seg>
<seg id="134"> Even the cowboys are pit crews now.  </seg>
<seg id="135"> And it seemed like time that we become that way ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="136"> Making systems work is the great task of my generation of physicians and scientists.  </seg>
<seg id="137"> But I would go further and say that making systems work, whether in health care, education, climate change, making a pathway out of poverty, is the great task of our generation as a whole.  </seg>
<seg id="138"> In every field, knowledge has exploded, but it has brought complexity, it has brought specialization.  </seg>
<seg id="139"> And we've come to a place where we have no choice but to recognize, as individualistic as we want to be, complexity requires group success.  </seg>
<seg id="140"> We all need to be pit crews now.  </seg>
<seg id="141"> Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1424" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/laura_carstensen_older_people_are_happier.html</url> 
<description>In the 20th century we added an unprecedented number of years to our lifespans, but is the quality of life as good? Surprisingly, yes! At TEDxWomen psychologist Laura Carstensen shows research that demonstrates that as people get older they become happier, more content, and have a more positive outlook on the world.</description> 
<keywords>aging,culture,science</keywords> 
<talkid>1424</talkid> 
<title>Laura Carstensen: Older people are happier</title> 
<seg id="1"> People are living longer and societies are getting grayer.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> You hear about it all the time.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> You read about it in your newspapers.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> You hear about it on your television sets.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> Sometimes I'm concerned that we hear about it so much that we've come to accept longer lives with a kind of a complacency, even ease.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> But make no mistake, longer lives can and, I believe, will improve quality of life at all ages.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> Now to put this in perspective, let me just zoom out for a minute.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> More years were added to average life expectancy in the 20th century than all years added across all prior millennia of human evolution combined. In the blink of an eye, we nearly doubled the length of time that we're living.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> So if you ever feel like you don't have this aging thing quite pegged, don't kick yourself.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> It's brand new.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> And because fertility rates fell across that very same period that life expectancy was going up, that pyramid that has always represented the distribution of age in the population, with many young ones at the bottom winnowed to a tiny peak of older people who make it and survive to old age is being reshaped into a rectangle.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> And now, if you're the kind of person who can get chills from population statistics, these are the ones that should do it.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> Because what that means is that for the first time in the history of the species, the majority of babies born in the Developed World are having the opportunity to grow old.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> How did this happen?  </seg>
<seg id="15"> Well we're no genetically hardier than our ancestors were 10,000 years ago.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> This increase in life expectancy is the remarkable product of culture -- the crucible that holds science and technology and wide-scale changes in behavior that improve health and well-being.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> Through cultural changes, our ancestors largely eliminated early death so that people can now live out their full lives.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> Now there are problems associated with aging -- diseases, poverty, loss of social status.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> It's hardly time to rest on our laurels.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> But the more we learn about aging, the clearer it becomes that a sweeping downward course is grossly inaccurate.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> Aging brings some rather remarkable improvements -- increased knowledge, expertise -- and emotional aspects of life improve.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> That's right, older people are happy.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> They're happier than middle-aged people, and younger people certainly.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> Study after study is coming to the same conclusion.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> The CDC recently conducted a survey where they asked respondents simply to tell them whether they experienced significant psychological distress in the previous week.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> And fewer older people answered affirmatively to that question than middle-aged people, and younger people as well.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> And a recent Gallup poll asked participants how much stress and worry and anger they had experienced the previous day.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> And stress, worry, anger all decrease with age.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> Now social scientists call this the paradox of aging.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> After all, aging is not a piece of cake.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> So we've asked all sorts of questions to see if we could undo this finding.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> We've asked whether it may be that the current generations of older people are and always have been the greatest generations.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> That is that younger people today may not typically experience these improvements as they grow older.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> We've asked, well maybe older people are just trying to put a positive spin on an otherwise depressing existence.  </seg>
<seg id="35">  But the more we've tried to disavow this finding, the more evidence we find to support it.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> Years ago, my colleagues and I embarked on a study where we followed the same group of people over a 10-year period.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> Originally the sample was aged 18 to 94.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> And we studied whether and how their emotional experiences changed as they grew older.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> Our participants would carry electronic pagers for a week at a time, and we'd page them throughout the day and evenings at random times.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> And every time we paged them we'd ask them to answer several questions -- On a one to seven scale, how happy are you right now?  </seg>
<seg id="41"> How sad are you right now?  </seg>
<seg id="42"> How frustrated are you right now? -- so that we could get a sense of the kinds of emotions and feelings they were having in their day-to-day lives.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> And using this intense study of individuals, we find that it's not one particular generation that's doing better than the others, but the same individuals over time come to report relatively greater positive experience.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> Now you see this slight downturn at very advanced ages.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> And there is a slight downturn.  </seg>
<seg id="46"> But at no point does it return to the levels we see in early adulthood.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> Now it's really too simplistic to say that older people are "happy."  </seg>
<seg id="48"> In our study, they are more positive, but they're also more likely than younger people to experience mixed emotions -- sadness at the same time you experience happiness; you know, that tear in the eye when you're smiling at a friend.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> And other research has shown that older people seem to engage with sadness more comfortably.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> They're more accepting of sadness than younger people are.  </seg>
<seg id="51"> And we suspect that this may help to explain why older people are better than younger people at solving hotly-charged emotional conflicts and debates.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> Older people can view injustice with compassion, but not despair.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> And all things being equal, older people direct their cognitive resources, like attention and memory, to positive information more than negative.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> If we show older, middle-aged, younger people images, like the ones you see on the screen, and we later ask them to recall all the images that they can, older people, but not younger people, remember more positive images than negative images.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> We've asked older and younger people to view faces in laboratory studies, some frowning, some smiling. Older people look toward the smiling faces and away from the frowning, angry faces.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> In day-to-day life, this translates into greater enjoyment and satisfaction.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> But as social scientists, we continue to ask about possible alternatives.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> We've said, well maybe older people report more positive emotions because they're cognitively impaired.  </seg>
<seg id="59">  We've said, could it be that positive emotions are simply easier to process than negative emotions, and so you switch to the positive emotions?  </seg>
<seg id="60"> Maybe our neural centers in our brain are degraded such that we're unable to process negative emotions anymore.  </seg>
<seg id="61"> But that's not the case.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> The most mentally sharp older adults are the ones who show this positivity effect the most.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> And under conditions where it really matters, older people do process the negative information just as well as the positive information.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> So how can this be?  </seg>
<seg id="65"> Well in our research, we've found that these changes are grounded fundamentally in the uniquely human ability to monitor time -- not just clock time and calendar time, but lifetime.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> And if there's a paradox of aging, it's that recognizing that we won't live forever changes our perspective on life in positive ways.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> When time horizons are long and nebulous, as they typically are in youth, people are constantly preparing, trying to soak up all the information they possibly can, taking risks, exploring.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> We might spend time with people we don't even like because it's somehow interesting.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> We might learn something unexpected.  </seg>
<seg id="70">  We go on blind dates.  </seg>
<seg id="71">  You know, after all, if it doesn't work out, there's always tomorrow.  </seg>
<seg id="72"> People over 50 don't go on blind dates.  </seg>
<seg id="73">  As we age, our time horizons grow shorter and our goals change.  </seg>
<seg id="74"> When we recognize that we don't have all the time in the world, we see our priorities most clearly.  </seg>
<seg id="75"> We take less notice of trivial matters.  </seg>
<seg id="76"> We savor life.  </seg>
<seg id="77"> We're more appreciative, more open to reconciliation.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> We invest in more emotionally important parts of life, and life gets better, so we're happier day-to-day.  </seg>
<seg id="79"> But that same shift in perspective leads us to have less tolerance than ever for injustice.  </seg>
<seg id="80"> By 2015, there will be more people in the United States over the age of 60 than under 15.  </seg>
<seg id="81"> What will happen to societies that are top-heavy with older people?  </seg>
<seg id="82"> The numbers won't determine the outcome.  </seg>
<seg id="83"> Culture will.  </seg>
<seg id="84"> If we invest in science and technology and find solutions for the real problems that older people face and we capitalize on the very real strengths of older people, then added years of life can dramatically improve quality of life at all ages.  </seg>
<seg id="85"> Societies with millions of talented, emotionally stable citizens who are healthier and better educated than any generations before them, armed with knowledge about the practical matters of life and motivated to solve the big issues can be better societies than we have ever known.  </seg>
<seg id="86"> My father, who is 92, likes to say, "Let's stop talking only about how to save the old folks and start talking about how to get them to save us all."  </seg>
<seg id="87"> Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1427" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/michael_norton_how_to_buy_happiness.html</url> 
<description>At TEDxCambridge, Michael Norton shares fascinating research on how money can, indeed buy happiness -- when you don't spend it on yourself. Listen for surprising data on the many ways pro-social spending can benefit you, your work, and  other people.</description> 
<keywords>business,community,money,philanthropy,psychology,shopping</keywords> 
<talkid>1427</talkid> 
<title>Michael Norton: How to buy happiness</title> 
<seg id="1"> So I want to talk today about money and happiness, which are two things that a lot of us spend a lot of our time thinking about, either trying to earn them or trying to increase them.  </seg>
<seg id="2"> And a lot of us resonate with this phrase.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> So we see it in religions and self-help books, that money can't buy happiness.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> And I want to suggest today that, in fact, that's wrong.  </seg>
<seg id="5">  I'm at a business school, so that's what we do.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> So that's wrong, and, in fact, if you think that, you're actually just not spending it right.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> So that instead of spending it the way you usually spend it, maybe if you spent it differently, that might work a little bit better.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> And before I tell you the ways that you can spend it that will make you happier, let's think about the ways we usually spend it that don't, in fact, make us happier.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> We had a little natural experiment.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> So CNN, a little while ago, wrote this interesting article on what happens to people when they win the lottery.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> It turns out people think when they win the lottery their lives are going to be amazing.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> This article's about how their lives get ruined.  </seg>
<seg id="13"> So what happens when people win the lottery is, number one, they spend all the money and go into debt, and number two, all of their friends and everyone they've ever met find them and bug them for money.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> And it ruins their social relationships, in fact.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> So they have more debt and worse friendships than they had before they won the lottery.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> What was interesting about the article was people started commenting on the article, readers of the thing.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> And instead of talking about how it had made them realize that money doesn't lead to happiness, everyone instantly started saying, "You know what I would do if I won the lottery ... ?" and fantasizing about what they'd do.  </seg>
<seg id="18"> And here's just two of the ones we saw that are just really interesting to think about.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> One person wrote in, "When I win, I'm going to buy my own little mountain and have a little house on top."  And another person wrote, "I would fill a big bathtub with money and get in the tub while smoking a big fat cigar and sipping a glass of champagne." This is even worse now: "Then I'd have a picture taken and dozens of glossies made.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> Anyone begging for money or trying to extort from me would receive a copy of the picture and nothing else."  And so many of the comments were exactly of this type, where people got money and, in fact, it made them antisocial.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> So I told you that it ruins people's lives and that their friends bug them.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> It also, money often makes us feel very selfish and we do things only for ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> Well maybe the reason that money doesn't make us happy is that we're always spending it on the wrong things, and in particular, that we're always spending it on ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> And we thought, I wonder what would happen if we made people spend more of their money on other people.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> So instead of being antisocial with your money, what if you were a little more prosocial with your money?  </seg>
<seg id="26"> And we thought, let's make people do it and see what happens.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> So let's have some people do what they usually do and spend money on themselves, and let's make some people give money away, and measure their happiness and see if, in fact, they get happier.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> So the first way that we did this.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> On one Vancouver morning, we went out on the campus at University of British Columbia and we approached people and said, "Do you want to be in an experiment?" They said, "Yes." We asked them how happy they were, and then we gave them an envelope.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> And one of the envelopes had things in it that said, "By 5:00 pm today, spend this money on yourself." So we gave some examples of what you could spend it on.  </seg>
<seg id="31"> Other people, in the morning, got a slip of paper that said, "By 5:00 pm today, spend this money on somebody else." Also inside the envelope was money.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> And we manipulated how much money we gave them.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> So some people got this slip of paper and five dollars.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> Some people got this slip of paper and 20 dollars.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> We let them go about their day. They did whatever they wanted to do.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> We found out that they did in fact spend it in the way that we asked them to.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> We called them up at night and asked them, "What'd you spend it on, and how happy do you feel now?" What did they spend it on?  </seg>
<seg id="38"> Well these are college undergrads, so a lot of what they spent it on for themselves were things like earrings and makeup.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> One woman said she bought a stuffed animal for her niece.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> People gave money to homeless people.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> Huge effect here of Starbucks.  </seg>
<seg id="42">  So if you give undergraduates five dollars, it looks like coffee to them and they run over to Starbucks and spend it as fast as they can.  </seg>
<seg id="43"> But some people bought a coffee for themselves, the way they usually would, but other people said that they bought a coffee for somebody else.  </seg>
<seg id="44"> So the very same purchase, just targeted toward yourself or targeted toward somebody else.  </seg>
<seg id="45"> What did we find when we called them back at the end of the day?  </seg>
<seg id="46"> People who spent money on other people got happier.  </seg>
<seg id="47"> People who spent money on themselves, nothing happened.  </seg>
<seg id="48"> It didn't make them less happy, it just didn't do much for them.  </seg>
<seg id="49"> And the other thing we saw is the amount of money doesn't matter that much.  </seg>
<seg id="50"> So people thought that 20 dollars would be way better than five dollars.  </seg>
<seg id="51"> In fact, it doesn't matter how much money you spent.  </seg>
<seg id="52"> What really matters is that you spent it on somebody else rather than on yourself.  </seg>
<seg id="53"> We see this again and again when we give people money to spend on other people instead of on themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="54"> Of course, these are undergraduates in Canada -- not the world's most representative population.  </seg>
<seg id="55"> They're also fairly wealthy and affluent and all these other sorts of things.  </seg>
<seg id="56"> We wanted to see if this holds true everywhere in the world or just among wealthy countries.  </seg>
<seg id="57"> So we went, in fact, to Uganda and ran a very similar experiment.  </seg>
<seg id="58"> So imagine, instead of just people in Canada, we said, "Name the last time you spent money on yourself or other people.  </seg>
<seg id="59"> Describe it. How happy did it make you?" Or in Uganda, "Name the last time you spent money on yourself or other people and describe that." And then we asked them how happy they are again.  </seg>
<seg id="60"> And what we see is sort of amazing because there's human universals on what you do with your money and then real cultural differences on what you do as well.  </seg>
<seg id="61"> So for example, one guy from Uganda says this.  </seg>
<seg id="62"> He said, "I called a girl I wished to love." They basically went out on a date, and he says at the end that he didn't "achieve" her up till now.  </seg>
<seg id="63"> Here's a guy from Canada.  </seg>
<seg id="64"> Very similar thing.  </seg>
<seg id="65"> "I took my girlfriend out for dinner.  </seg>
<seg id="66"> We went to a movie, we left early, and then went back to her room for ... " only cake -- just a piece of cake.  </seg>
<seg id="67"> Human universal -- so you spend money on other people, you're being nice to them.  </seg>
<seg id="68"> Maybe you have something in mind, maybe not.  </seg>
<seg id="69"> But then we see extraordinary differences.  </seg>
<seg id="70"> So look at these two.  </seg>
<seg id="71"> This is a woman from Canada.  </seg>
<seg id="72"> We say, "Name a time you spent money on somebody else." She says, "I bought a present for my mom.  </seg>
<seg id="73"> I drove to the mall in my car, bought a present, gave it to my mom." Perfectly nice thing to do.  </seg>
<seg id="74"> It's good to get gifts for people that you know.  </seg>
<seg id="75"> Compare that to this woman from Uganda.  </seg>
<seg id="76"> "I was walking and met a long-time friend whose son was sick with malaria.  </seg>
<seg id="77"> They had no money, they went to a clinic and I gave her this money." This isn't $10,000, it's the local currency.  </seg>
<seg id="78"> So it's a very small amount of money, in fact.  </seg>
<seg id="79"> But enormously different motivations here.  </seg>
<seg id="80"> This is a real medical need, literally a life-saving donation.  </seg>
<seg id="81"> Above, it's just kind of, I bought a gift for my mother.  </seg>
<seg id="82"> What we see again though is that the specific way that you spend on other people isn't nearly as important as the fact that you spend on other people in order to make yourself happy, which is really quite important.  </seg>
<seg id="83"> So you don't have to do amazing things with your money to make yourself happy.  </seg>
<seg id="84"> You can do small, trivial things and yet still get these benefits from doing this.  </seg>
<seg id="85"> These are only two countries.  </seg>
<seg id="86"> We also wanted to go even broader and look at every country in the world if we could to see what the relationship is between money and happiness.  </seg>
<seg id="87"> We got data from the Gallup Organization, which you know from all the political polls that have been happening lately.  </seg>
<seg id="88"> They ask people, "Did you donate money to charity recently?" and they ask them, "How happy are you with your life in general?" And we can see what the relationship is between those two things.  </seg>
<seg id="89"> Are they positively correlated? Giving money makes you happy.  </seg>
<seg id="90"> Or are they negatively correlated?  </seg>
<seg id="91"> On this map, green will mean they're positively correlated and red means they're negatively correlated.  </seg>
<seg id="92"> And you can see, the world is crazily green.  </seg>
<seg id="93"> So in almost every country in the world where we have this data, people who give money to charity are happier people that people who don't give money to charity.  </seg>
<seg id="94"> I know you're all looking at that red country in the middle.  </seg>
<seg id="95"> I would be a jerk and not tell you what it is, but in fact, it's Central African Republic.  </seg>
<seg id="96"> You can make up stories. Maybe it's different there for some reason or another.  </seg>
<seg id="97"> Just below that to the right is Rwanda though, which is amazingly green.  </seg>
<seg id="98"> So almost everywhere we look we see that giving money away makes you happier than keeping it for yourself.  </seg>
<seg id="99"> What about your work life, which is where we spend all the rest of our time when we're not with the people we know.  </seg>
<seg id="100"> We decided to infiltrate some companies and do a very similar thing.  </seg>
<seg id="101"> So these are sales teams in Belgium.  </seg>
<seg id="102"> They work in teams; they go out and sell to doctors and try to get them to buy drugs.  </seg>
<seg id="103"> So we can look and see how well they sell things as a function of being a member of a team.  </seg>
<seg id="104"> Some teams, we give people on the team some money for themselves and say, "Spend it however you want on yourself," just like we did with the undergrads in Canada.  </seg>
<seg id="105"> But other teams we say, "Here's 15 euro.  </seg>
<seg id="106"> Spend it on one of your teammates this week.  </seg>
<seg id="107"> Buy them something as a gift or a present and give it to them.  </seg>
<seg id="108"> And then we can see, well now we've got teams that spend on themselves and we've got these prosocial teams who we give money to make the team a little bit better.  </seg>
<seg id="109"> The reason I have a ridiculous pinata there is one of the teams pooled their money and bought a pinata, and they all got around and smashed the pinata and all the candy fell out and things like that.  </seg>
<seg id="110"> A very silly, trivial thing to do, but think of the difference on a team that didn't do that at all, that got 15 euro, put it in their pocket, maybe bought themselves a coffee, or teams that had this prosocial experience where they all bonded together to buy something and do a group activity.  </seg>
<seg id="111"> What we see is that, in fact, the teams that are prosocial sell more stuff than the teams that only got money for themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="112"> And one way to think about it is for every 15 euro you give people for themselves, they put it in their pocket, they don't do anything different than they did before.  </seg>
<seg id="113"> You don't get any money from that.  </seg>
<seg id="114"> You actually lose money because it doesn't motivate them to perform any better.  </seg>
<seg id="115"> But when you give them 15 euro to spend on their teammates, they do so much better on their teams that you actually get a huge win on investing this kind of money.  </seg>
<seg id="116"> And I realize that you're probably thinking to yourselves, this is all fine, but there's a context that's incredibly important for public policy and I can't imagine it would work there.  </seg>
<seg id="117"> And basically that if he doesn't show me that it works here, I don't believe anything he said.  </seg>
<seg id="118"> And I know what you're all thinking about are dodgeball teams.  </seg>
<seg id="119">  This was a huge criticism that we got to say, if you can't show it with dodgeball teams, this is all stupid.  </seg>
<seg id="120"> So we went out and found these dodgeball teams and infiltrated them.  </seg>
<seg id="121"> And we did the exact same thing as before.  </seg>
<seg id="122"> So some teams, we give people on the team money, they spend it on themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="123"> Other teams, we give them money to spend on their dodgeball teammates.  </seg>
<seg id="124"> The teams that spend money on themselves are just the same winning percentages as they were before.  </seg>
<seg id="125"> The teams that we give the money to spend on each other, they become different teams and, in fact, they dominate the league by the time they're done.  </seg>
<seg id="126"> Across all of these different contexts -- your personal life, you work life, even silly things like intramural sports -- we see spending on other people has a bigger return for you than spending on yourself.  </seg>
<seg id="127"> And so I'll just say, I think if you think money can't buy happiness you're not spending it right.  </seg>
<seg id="128"> The implication is not you should buy this product instead of that product and that's the way to make yourself happier.  </seg>
<seg id="129"> It's in fact, that you should stop thinking about which product to buy for yourself and try giving some of it to other people instead.  </seg>
<seg id="130"> And we luckily have an opportunity for you.  </seg>
<seg id="131"> DonorsChoose.org is a non-profit for mainly public school teachers in low-income schools.  </seg>
<seg id="132"> They post projects, so they say, "I want to teach Huckleberry Finn to my class and we don't have the books," or "I want a microscope to teach my students science and we don't have a microscope."  </seg>
<seg id="133"> You and I can go on and buy it for them.  </seg>
<seg id="134"> The teacher writes you a thank you note. The kids write you a thank you note.  </seg>
<seg id="135"> Sometimes they send you pictures of them using the microscope.  </seg>
<seg id="136"> It's an extraordinary thing.  </seg>
<seg id="137"> Go to the website and start yourself on the process of thinking, again, less about "How can I spend money on myself?" and more about "If I've got five dollars or 15 dollars, what can I do to benefit other people?" Because ultimately when you do that, you'll find that you'll benefit yourself much more.  </seg>
<seg id="138"> Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1425" genre="lectures">
<url>http://www.ted.com/talks/christina_warinner_tracking_ancient_diseases_using_plaque.html</url> 
<description>Imagine what we could learn about diseases by studying the history of human disease, from ancient hominids to the present. But how? TED Fellow Christina Warinner is an achaeological geneticist, and she's found a spectacular new tool -- the microbial DNA in fossilized dental plaque.</description> 
<keywords>evolution,medicine,paleontology,science</keywords> 
<talkid>1425</talkid> 
<title>Christina Warinner: Tracking ancient diseases using ... plaque</title> 
<seg id="1"> Have you ever wondered what is inside your dental plaque?  </seg>
<seg id="2"> Probably not, but people like me do.  </seg>
<seg id="3"> I'm an archeological geneticist at the Center for Evolutionary Medicine at the University of Zurich, and I study the origins and evolution of human health and disease by conducting genetic research on the skeletal and mummified remains of ancient humans.  </seg>
<seg id="4"> And through this work, I hope to better understand the evolutionary vulnerabilities of our bodies, so that we can improve and better manage our health in the future.  </seg>
<seg id="5"> There are different ways to approach evolutionary medicine, and one way is to extract human DNA from ancient bones.  </seg>
<seg id="6"> And from these extracts, we can reconstruct the human genome at different points in time and look for changes that might be related to adaptations, risk factors and inherited diseases.  </seg>
<seg id="7"> But this is only one half of the story.  </seg>
<seg id="8"> The most important health challenges today are not caused by simple mutations in our genome, but rather result from a complex and dynamic interplay between genetic variation, diet, microbes and parasites and our immune response.  </seg>
<seg id="9"> All of these diseases have a strong evolutionary component that directly relates to the fact that we live today in a very different environment than the ones in which our bodies evolved.  </seg>
<seg id="10"> And in order to understand these diseases, we need to move past studies of the human genome alone and towards a more holistic approach to human health in the past.  </seg>
<seg id="11"> But there are a lot of challenges for this.  </seg>
<seg id="12"> And first of all, what do we even study?  </seg>
<seg id="13"> Skeletons are ubiquitous; they're found all over the place.  </seg>
<seg id="14"> But of course, all of the soft tissue has decomposed, and the skeleton itself has limited health information.  </seg>
<seg id="15"> Mummies are a great source of information, except that they're really geographically limited and limited in time as well.  </seg>
<seg id="16"> Coprolites are fossilized human feces, and they're actually extremely interesting.  </seg>
<seg id="17"> You can learn a lot about ancient diet and intestinal disease, but they are very rare.  </seg>
<seg id="18">  So to address this problem, I put together a team of international researchers in Switzerland, Denmark and the U.K.  </seg>
<seg id="19"> to study a very poorly studied, little known material that's found on people everywhere.  </seg>
<seg id="20"> It's a type of fossilized dental plaque that is called officially dental calculus.  </seg>
<seg id="21"> Many of you may know it by the term tartar.  </seg>
<seg id="22"> It's what the dentist cleans off your teeth every time that you go in for a visit.  </seg>
<seg id="23"> And in a typical dentistry visit, you may have about 15 to 30 milligrams removed.  </seg>
<seg id="24"> But in ancient times before tooth brushing, up to 600 milligrams might have built up on the teeth over a lifetime.  </seg>
<seg id="25"> And what's really important about dental calculus is that it fossilizes just like the rest of the skeleton, it's abundant in quantity before the present day and it's ubiquitous worldwide.  </seg>
<seg id="26"> We find it in every population around the world at all time periods going back tens of thousands of years.  </seg>
<seg id="27"> And we even find it in neanderthals and animals.  </seg>
<seg id="28"> And so previous studies had only focused on microscopy.  </seg>
<seg id="29"> They'd looked at dental calculus under a microscope, and what they had found was things like pollen and plant starches, and they'd found muscle cells from animal meats and bacteria.  </seg>
<seg id="30"> And so what my team of researchers, what we wanted to do, is say, can we apply genetic and proteomic technology to go after DNA and proteins, and from this can we get better taxonomic resolution to really understand what's going on?  </seg>
<seg id="31"> And what we found is that we can find many commensal and pathogenic bacteria that inhabited the nasal passages and mouth.  </seg>
<seg id="32"> We also have found immune proteins related to infection and inflammation and proteins and DNA related to diet.  </seg>
<seg id="33"> But what was surprising to us, and also quite exciting, is we also found bacteria that normally inhabit upper respiratory systems.  </seg>
<seg id="34"> So it gives us virtual access to the lungs, which is where many important diseases reside.  </seg>
<seg id="35"> And we also found bacteria that normally inhabit the gut.  </seg>
<seg id="36"> And so we can also now virtually gain access to this even more distant organ system that, from the skeleton alone, has long decomposed.  </seg>
<seg id="37"> And so by applying ancient DNA sequencing and protein mass spectrometry technologies to ancient dental calculus, we can generate immense quantities of data that then we can use to begin to reconstruct a detailed picture of the dynamic interplay between diet, infection and immunity thousands of years ago.  </seg>
<seg id="38"> So what started out as an idea, is now being implemented to churn out millions of sequences that we can use to investigate the long-term evolutionary history of human health and disease, right down to the genetic code of individual pathogens.  </seg>
<seg id="39"> And from this information we can learn about how pathogens evolve and also why they continue to make us sick.  </seg>
<seg id="40"> And I hope I have convinced you of the value of dental calculus.  </seg>
<seg id="41"> And as a final parting thought, on behalf of future archeologists, I would like to ask you to please think twice before you go home and brush your teeth.  </seg>
</doc>
</srcset>
</mteval>
