<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mteval>
<srcset setid="iwslt2012-tst2011" srclang="english">
<doc docid="1175" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/daniel_tammet_different_ways_of_knowing.html</url>
    <description>Daniel Tammet has linguistic, numerical and visual synesthesia -- meaning that his perception of words, numbers and colors are woven together into a new way of perceiving and understanding the world. The author of "Born on a Blue Day," Tammet shares his art and his passion for languages in this glimpse into his beautiful mind.</description>
    <keywords>Arts,Culture,brain</keywords>
    <talkid>1175</talkid>
    <title>Daniel Tammet: Different ways of knowing</title>
<seg id="1">  I'm a savant,  or more precisely,  a high-functioning  autistic savant.  </seg>
<seg id="2">  It's a rare condition.  </seg>
<seg id="3">  And rarer still when accompanied,  as in my case,  by self-awareness  and a mastery of language.  </seg>
<seg id="4">  Very often when I meet someone  and they learn this about me  there's a certain kind of awkwardness.  </seg>
<seg id="5">  I can see it in their eyes.  </seg>
<seg id="6">  They want to ask me something.  </seg>
<seg id="7">  And in the end, quite often,  the urge is stronger than they are  and they blurt it out:  "If I give you my date of birth,  can you tell me what day of the week I was born on?"  </seg>
<seg id="8">  Or they mention cube roots  or ask me to recite a long number or long text.  </seg>
<seg id="9">  I hope you'll forgive me  if I don't perform  a kind of one-man savant show for you today.  </seg>
<seg id="10">  I'm going to talk instead  about something  far more interesting  than dates of birth or cube roots --  a little deeper  and a lot closer, to my mind, than work.  </seg>
<seg id="11">  I want to talk to you briefly  about perception.  </seg>
<seg id="12">  When he was writing the plays and the short stories  that would make his name,  Anton Chekhov kept a notebook  in which he noted down  his observations  of the world around him --  little details  that other people seem to miss.  </seg>
<seg id="13">  Every time I read Chekhov  and his unique vision of human life,  I'm reminded of why I too  became a writer.  </seg>
<seg id="14">  In my books,  I explore the nature of perception  and how different kinds of perceiving  create different kinds of knowing  and understanding.  </seg>
<seg id="15">  Here are three questions  drawn from my work.  </seg>
<seg id="16">  Rather than try to figure them out,  I'm going to ask you to consider for a moment  the intuitions  and the gut instincts  that are going through your head and your heart  as you look at them.  </seg>
<seg id="17">  For example, the calculation.  </seg>
<seg id="18">  Can you feel where on the number line  the solution is likely to fall?  </seg>
<seg id="19">  Or look at the foreign word and the sounds.  </seg>
<seg id="20">  Can you get a sense of the range of meanings  that it's pointing you towards?  </seg>
<seg id="21">  And in terms of the line of poetry,  why does the poet use the word hare  rather than rabbit?  </seg>
<seg id="22">  I'm asking you to do this  because I believe our personal perceptions, you see,  are at the heart  of how we acquire knowledge.  </seg>
<seg id="23">  Aesthetic judgments,  rather than abstract reasoning,  guide and shape the process  by which we all come to know  what we know.  </seg>
<seg id="24">  I'm an extreme example of this.  </seg>
<seg id="25">  My worlds of words and numbers  blur with color, emotion  and personality.  </seg>
<seg id="26">  As Juan said,  it's the condition that scientists call synesthesia,  an unusual cross-talk  between the senses.  </seg>
<seg id="27">  Here are the numbers one to 12  as I see them --  every number with its own shape and character.  </seg>
<seg id="28">  One is a flash of white light.  </seg>
<seg id="29">  Six is a tiny and very sad black hole.  </seg>
<seg id="30">  The sketches are in black and white here,  but in my mind they have colors.  </seg>
<seg id="31">  Three is green.  </seg>
<seg id="32">  Four is blue.  </seg>
<seg id="33">  Five is yellow.  </seg>
<seg id="34">  I paint as well.  </seg>
<seg id="35">  And here is one of my paintings.  </seg>
<seg id="36">  It's a multiplication of two prime numbers.  </seg>
<seg id="37">  Three-dimensional shapes  and the space they create in the middle  creates a new shape,  the answer to the sum.  </seg>
<seg id="38">  What about bigger numbers?  </seg>
<seg id="39">  Well you can't get much bigger than Pi,  the mathematical constant.  </seg>
<seg id="40">  It's an infinite number --  literally goes on forever.  </seg>
<seg id="41">  In this painting that I made  of the first 20 decimals of Pi,  I take the colors  and the emotions and the textures  and I pull them all together  into a kind of rolling numerical landscape.  </seg>
<seg id="42">  But it's not only numbers that I see in colors.  </seg>
<seg id="43">  Words too, for me,  have colors and emotions  and textures.  </seg>
<seg id="44">  And this is an opening phrase  from the novel "Lolita."  </seg>
<seg id="45">  And Nabokov was himself synesthetic.  </seg>
<seg id="46">  And you can see here  how my perception of the sound L  helps the alliteration  to jump right out.  </seg>
<seg id="47">  Another example:  a little bit more mathematical.  </seg>
<seg id="48">  And I wonder if some of you will notice  the construction of the sentence  from "The Great Gatsby."  </seg>
<seg id="49">  There is a procession of syllables --  wheat, one;  prairies, two;  lost Swede towns, three --  one, two, three.  </seg>
<seg id="50">  And this effect is very pleasant on the mind,  and it helps the sentence  to feel right.  </seg>
<seg id="51">  Let's go back to the questions  I posed you a moment ago.  </seg>
<seg id="52">  64 multiplied by 75.  </seg>
<seg id="53">  If some of you play chess,  you'll know that 64  is a square number,  and that's why chessboards,  eight by eight,  have 64 squares.  </seg>
<seg id="54">  So that gives us a form  that we can picture, that we can perceive.  </seg>
<seg id="55">  What about 75?  </seg>
<seg id="56">  Well if 100,  if we think of 100 as being like a square,  75 would look like this.  </seg>
<seg id="57">  So what we need to do now  is put those two pictures  together in our mind --  something like this.  </seg>
<seg id="58">  64 becomes 6,400.  </seg>
<seg id="59">  And in the right-hand corner,  you don't have to calculate anything.  </seg>
<seg id="60">  Four across, four up and down --  it's 16.  </seg>
<seg id="61">  So what the sum is actually asking you to do  is 16,  16, 16.  </seg>
<seg id="62">  That's a lot easier  than the school taught you to do math, I'm sure.  </seg>
<seg id="63">  It's 16, 16, 16, 48,  4,800 --  4,000,  the answer to the sum.  </seg>
<seg id="64">  Easy when you know how.  </seg>
<seg id="65">  The second question was an Icelandic word.  </seg>
<seg id="66">  I'm assuming there are not many people here  who speak Icelandic.  </seg>
<seg id="67">  So let me narrow the choices down to two.  </seg>
<seg id="68">  is it a happy word,  or a sad word?  </seg>
<seg id="69">  What do you say?  </seg>
<seg id="70">  Okay.  </seg>
<seg id="71">  Some people say it's happy.  </seg>
<seg id="72">  Most people, a majority of people,  say sad.  </seg>
<seg id="73">  And it actually means sad.  </seg>
<seg id="74">  Why do, statistically,  a majority of people  say that a word is sad, in this case,  heavy in other cases?  </seg>
<seg id="75">  In my theory, language evolves in such a way  that sounds match,  correspond with the subjective,  with the personal  intuitive experience  of the listener.  </seg>
<seg id="76">  Let's have a look at the third question.  </seg>
<seg id="77">  It's a line from a poem by John Keats.  </seg>
<seg id="78">  Words, like numbers,  express fundamental relationships  between objects  and events and forces  that constitute our world.  </seg>
<seg id="79">  It stands to reason that we, existing in this world,  should in the course of our lives  absorb intuitively those relationships.  </seg>
<seg id="80">  And poets, like other artists,  play with those intuitive understandings.  </seg>
<seg id="81">  In the case of hare,  it's an ambiguous sound in English.  </seg>
<seg id="82">  It can also mean the fibers that grow from a head.  </seg>
<seg id="83">  And if we think of that --  let me put the picture up --  the fibers represent vulnerability.  </seg>
<seg id="84">  They yield to the slightest movement  or motion or emotion.  </seg>
<seg id="85">  So what you have is an atmosphere  of vulnerability and tension.  </seg>
<seg id="86">  The hare itself, the animal --  not a cat, not a dog, a hare --  why a hare?  </seg>
<seg id="87">  Because think of the picture,  not the word, the picture.  </seg>
<seg id="88">  The overlong ears,  the overlarge feet,  helps us to picture, to feel intuitively,  what it means to limp  and to tremble.  </seg>
<seg id="89">  So in these few minutes,  I hope I've been able to share  a little bit of my vision of things,  and to show you  that words can have colors and emotions,  numbers, shapes and personalities.  </seg>
<seg id="90">  The world is richer,  vaster  than it too often seems to be.  </seg>
<seg id="91">  I hope that I've given you the desire  to learn to see the world with new eyes.  </seg>
<seg id="92">  Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1169" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/shea_hembrey_how_i_became_100_artists.html</url>
    <description>How do you stage an international art show with work from 100 different artists? If you're Shea Hembrey, you invent all of the artists and artwork yourself -- from large-scale outdoor installations to tiny paintings drawn with a single-haired brush. Watch this funny, mind-bending talk to see the explosion of creativity and diversity of skills a single artist is capable of.</description>
    <keywords>Arts,Design,art,creativity,storytelling</keywords>
    <talkid>1169</talkid>
    <title>Shea Hembrey: How I became 100 artists</title>
<seg id="93">  I'm a contemporary artist  with a bit of an unexpected background.  </seg>
<seg id="94">  I was in my 20s before I ever went to an art museum.  </seg>
<seg id="95">  I grew up in the middle of nowhere  on a dirt road in rural Arkansas,  an hour from the nearest movie theater.  </seg>
<seg id="96">  And I think it was a great place to grow up as an artist,  because I grew up around quirky, colorful characters  who were great at making with their hands.  </seg>
<seg id="97">  And my childhood is more hick  than I could ever possibly relate to you,  and also more intellectual than you would ever expect.  </seg>
<seg id="98">  For instance, me and my sister, when we were little,  we would compete to see who could eat the most squirrel brains.  </seg>
<seg id="99">  But on the other side of that though,  we were big readers in our house.  </seg>
<seg id="100">  And if the TV was on, we were watching a documentary.  </seg>
<seg id="101">  And my dad is the most voracious reader I know.  </seg>
<seg id="102">  He can read a novel or two a day.  </seg>
<seg id="103">  But when I was little, I remember,  he would kill flies in our house with my BB gun.  </seg>
<seg id="104">  And what was so amazing to me about that --  well he would be in his recliner, would holler for me to fetch the BB gun,  and I'd go get it.  </seg>
<seg id="105">  And what was amazing to me --  well it was pretty kickass; he was killing a fly in the house with a gun --  but what was so amazing to me  was that he knew just enough how to pump it.  </seg>
<seg id="106">  And he could shoot it from two rooms away  and not damage what it was on,  because he knew how to pump it just enough to kill the fly  and not damage what it landed on.  </seg>
<seg id="107">  So I should talk about art.  </seg>
<seg id="108">  Or we'll be here all day with my childhood stories.  </seg>
<seg id="109">  I love contemporary art,  but I'm often really frustrated with the contemporary art world  and the contemporary art scene.  </seg>
<seg id="110">  A few years ago,  I spent months in Europe  to see the major international art exhibitions  that have the pulse  of what is supposed to be going on in the art world.  </seg>
<seg id="111">  And I was struck  by going to so many, one after the other,  with some clarity of what it was  that I was longing for.  </seg>
<seg id="112">  And I was longing for several things that I wasn't getting,  or not getting enough of.  </seg>
<seg id="113">  But two of the main things:  one of it, I was longing for more work  that was appealing to a broad public,  that was accessible.  </seg>
<seg id="114">  And the second thing that I was longing for  was some more exquisite craftsmanship  and technique.  </seg>
<seg id="115">  So I started thinking and listing  what all it was that I thought would make a perfect biennial.  </seg>
<seg id="116">  So I decided,  I'm going to start my own biennial.  </seg>
<seg id="117">  I'm going to organize it and direct it  and get it going in the world.  </seg>
<seg id="118">  So I thought, okay,  I have to have some criteria of how to choose work.  </seg>
<seg id="119">  So amongst all the criteria I have,  there's two main things.  </seg>
<seg id="120">  One of them, I call my Mimaw's Test.  </seg>
<seg id="121">  And what that is  is I imagine explaining a work of art  to my grandmother in five minutes.  </seg>
<seg id="122">  And if I can explain it in five minutes,  then it's too obtuse  or esoteric  and it hasn't been refined enough yet.  </seg>
<seg id="123">  It needs to worked on  until it can speak fluently.  </seg>
<seg id="124">  And then my other second set of rules --  I hate to say "rules" because it's art --  my criteria would be  the three H's,  which is head, heart and hands.  </seg>
<seg id="125">  And great art would have head:  it would have interesting intellectual ideas  and concepts.  </seg>
<seg id="126">  It would have heart in that it would have passion  and heart and soul.  </seg>
<seg id="127">  And it would have hand in that it would be greatly crafted.  </seg>
<seg id="128">  So I started thinking about  how am I going to do this biennial,  how am I going to travel the world  and find these artists.  </seg>
<seg id="129">  And then I realized one day, there's an easier solution to this.  </seg>
<seg id="130">  I'm just going to make the whole thing myself.  </seg>
<seg id="131">  And so this is what I did.  </seg>
<seg id="132">  So I thought, a biennial needs artists.  </seg>
<seg id="133">  I'm going to do an international biennial, I need artists from all around the world.  </seg>
<seg id="134">  So what I did was  I invented a hundred artists from around the world.  </seg>
<seg id="135">  I figured out their bios, their their passions in life  and their art styles,  and I started making their work.  </seg>
<seg id="136">  I felt, oh this is the kind of project that I could spend my whole life doing.  </seg>
<seg id="137">  So I decided, I'm going to make this a real biennial.  </seg>
<seg id="138">  It's going to be two years of studio work.  </seg>
<seg id="139">  And I'm going to create this in two years.  </seg>
<seg id="140">  And I have.  </seg>
<seg id="141">  So I should start to talk about these guys.  </seg>
<seg id="142">  Well the range is quite a bit.  </seg>
<seg id="143">  And I'm such a technician, so I loved project,  getting to play with all the techniques.  </seg>
<seg id="144">  So for example, in realist paintings,  it ranges from this,  which is kind of old masters style,  to really realistic still-life,  to this type of painting where I'm painting with a single hair.  </seg>
<seg id="145">  And then at the other end, there's performance and short films  and indoor installations  like this indoor installation  and this one,  and outdoor installations like this one  and this one.  </seg>
<seg id="146">  I know I should mention, I'm making all these things.  </seg>
<seg id="147">  This isn't Photoshopped.  </seg>
<seg id="148">  I'm under the river with those fish.  </seg>
<seg id="149">  So now let me introduce some of my fictional artists to you.  </seg>
<seg id="150">  This is Nell Remmel.  </seg>
<seg id="151">  Nell is interested in agricultural processes,  and her work is based in these practices.  </seg>
<seg id="152">  This piece, which is called "Flipped Earth" --  she was interested in taking the sky  and using it to cleanse barren ground.  </seg>
<seg id="153">  And by taking giant mirrors --  And here she's taking giant mirrors  and pulling them into the dirt.  </seg>
<seg id="154">  And this is 22 ft. long.  </seg>
<seg id="155">  And what I loved about her work  is, when I would walk around it  and look down into the sky,  looking down to watch the sky,  and it unfolded in a new way.  </seg>
<seg id="156">  And probably the best part of this piece  is at dusk and dawn  when the twilight wedge has fallen and the ground's dark,  but there's still the light above, bright above.  </seg>
<seg id="157">  And so you're standing there and everything else is dark,  but there's this portal that you want to jump in.  </seg>
<seg id="158">  This piece was great. This is in my parents' backyard in Arkansas.  </seg>
<seg id="159">  And I love to dig a hole.  </seg>
<seg id="160">  So this piece was great fun,  because it was two days of digging in soft dirt.  </seg>
<seg id="161">  The next artist is Kay Overstry,  and she's interested in ephemerality and transience.  </seg>
<seg id="162">  And in her most recent project,  it's called "Weather I Made."  </seg>
<seg id="163">  And she's making weather  on her body's scale.  </seg>
<seg id="164">  And this piece is "Frost."  </seg>
<seg id="165">  And what she did was she went out on a cold, dry night  and breathed back and forth on the lawn  to leave --  to leave her life's mark,  the mark of her life.  </seg>
<seg id="166">  And so this is five foot, five inches of frost  that she left behind.  </seg>
<seg id="167">  The sun rises, and it melts away.  </seg>
<seg id="168">  And that was played by my mom.  </seg>
<seg id="169">  So the next artist, this is a group of Japanese artists,  a collective of Japanese artists --  in Tokyo.  </seg>
<seg id="170">  And they were interested in developing a new, alternative art space.  </seg>
<seg id="171">  And they needed funding for it,  so they decided to come up with some interesting fundraising projects.  </seg>
<seg id="172">  One of these is scratch-off masterpieces.  </seg>
<seg id="173">  And so what they're doing --  each of these artists on a nine by seven-inch card,  which they sell for 10 bucks,  they drew original works of art.  </seg>
<seg id="174">  And you buy one, and maybe you get a real piece, and maybe not.  </seg>
<seg id="175">  Well this has sparked a craze in Japan,  because everyone's wanting a masterpiece.  </seg>
<seg id="176">  And the ones that are the most sought after  are the ones that are only barely scratched off.  </seg>
<seg id="177">  And all these works, in some way,  talk about luck or fate or chance.  </seg>
<seg id="178">  Those first two  are portraits of mega-jackpot winners years before and after their win.  </seg>
<seg id="179">  And in this one it's called "Drawing the Short Stick."  </seg>
<seg id="180">  I love these piece because I have a little cousin at home  who introduced me -- which I think is such a great introduction --  to a friend one day as, "This is my cousin Shea.  </seg>
<seg id="181">  He draws sticks real good."  </seg>
<seg id="182">  Which is one of the best compliments ever.  </seg>
<seg id="183">  This artist is Gus Weinmueller,  and he's doing a project, a large project, called "Art for the Peoples."  </seg>
<seg id="184">  And within this project, he's doing a smaller project  called "Artists in Residence."  </seg>
<seg id="185">  And what he does is --  he spends a week at a time with a family.  </seg>
<seg id="186">  And he shows up on their porch, their doorstep,  with a toothbrush and pajamas,  and he's ready to spend the week with them.  </seg>
<seg id="187">  And using only what's present,  he goes in and makes a little abode studio to work out of.  </seg>
<seg id="188">  And he spends that week talking to the family  about what do they think great art is.  </seg>
<seg id="189">  He has all these discussions with their family.  </seg>
<seg id="190">  And he digs through everything they have,  and he finds materials to make work.  </seg>
<seg id="191">  And he makes a work  that answers what they think great art is.  </seg>
<seg id="192">  For this family, he made this still-life painting.  </seg>
<seg id="193">  And whatever he makes  somehow references nesting and space  and personal property.  </seg>
<seg id="194">  This next project,  this is by Jaochim Parisvega,  and he's interested in --  He believes art is everywhere waiting --  that it just needs a little bit of a push to happen.  </seg>
<seg id="195">  And he provides this push by harnessing natural forces,  like in his series where he used rain to make paintings.  </seg>
<seg id="196">  This project is called "Love Nests."  </seg>
<seg id="197">  What he did was to get wild birds to make his art for him.  </seg>
<seg id="198">  So he put the material in places where the birds were going to collect them,  and they crafted his nests for him.  </seg>
<seg id="199">  And this one's called "Lovelock's Nest."  </seg>
<seg id="200">  This one's called "Mixtape Love Song's Nest."  </seg>
<seg id="201">  And this one's called "Lovemaking Nest."  </seg>
<seg id="202">  Next is Sylvia Slater.  </seg>
<seg id="203">  Sylvia's interested in art training.  </seg>
<seg id="204">  She's a very serious Swiss artist.  </seg>
<seg id="205">  And she was thinking about her friends and family  who work in chaos-ridden places and developing countries,  and she was thinking,  what can I make that would be of value to them,  in case something bad happens  and they have to buy their way across the border  or pay off a gunman.  </seg>
<seg id="206">  And so she came up with creating  these pocket-sized artworks  that are portraits of the person that would carry them.  </seg>
<seg id="207">  And you would carry this around with you,  and if everything went to hell, you could make payments  and buy your life.  </seg>
<seg id="208">  So this life price  is for an irrigation non-profit director.  </seg>
<seg id="209">  So hopefully what happens is you never use it,  and it's an heirloom that you pass down.  </seg>
<seg id="210">  And she makes them so they could either be broken up into payments,  or they could be like these, which are leaves that can be payments.  </seg>
<seg id="211">  And so they're valuable. This is precious metals and gemstones.  </seg>
<seg id="212">  And this one had to get broken up.  </seg>
<seg id="213">  He had to break off a piece to get out of Egypt recently.  </seg>
<seg id="214">  This is by a duo, Michael Abernathy and Bud Holland.  </seg>
<seg id="215">  And they're interested in creating culture,  just tradition.  </seg>
<seg id="216">  So what they do is they move into an area  and try to establish a new tradition in a small geographic area.  </seg>
<seg id="217">  So this is in Eastern Tennessee,  and what they decided was  that we need a positive tradition  that goes with death.  </seg>
<seg id="218">  So they came up with dig jigs.  </seg>
<seg id="219">  And a dig jig --  a dig jig is where,  for a milestone anniversary or a birthday,  you gather all your friends and family together  and you dance on where you're going to be buried.  </seg>
<seg id="220">  And we got a lot of attention when we did it.  </seg>
<seg id="221">  I talked my family into doing this, and they didn't know what I was doing.  </seg>
<seg id="222">  And I was like, "Get dressed for a funeral. We're going to go do some work."  </seg>
<seg id="223">  And so we got to the grave and made this, which was hilarious --  the attention that we got.  </seg>
<seg id="224">  So what happens is you dance on the grave.  </seg>
<seg id="225">  And after you've done your dance,  everyone toasts you and tells you how great you are.  </seg>
<seg id="226">  And you in essence have a funeral  that you get to be present for.  </seg>
<seg id="227">  That's my mom and dad.  </seg>
<seg id="228">  This is by Jason Birdsong.  </seg>
<seg id="229">  He is interested in how we see as an animal,  how we are interested in mimicry and camouflage.  </seg>
<seg id="230">  You know, we look down a dark alley  or a jungle path,  trying to make out a face or a creature.  </seg>
<seg id="231">  We just have that natural way of seeing.  </seg>
<seg id="232">  And he plays with this idea.  </seg>
<seg id="233">  And this piece: those aren't actually leaves.  </seg>
<seg id="234">  They're butterfly specimens who have a natural camouflage.  </seg>
<seg id="235">  So he pairs these up.  </seg>
<seg id="236">  There's another pile of leaves.  </seg>
<seg id="237">  Those are actually all real butterfly specimens.  </seg>
<seg id="238">  And he pairs these up with paintings.  </seg>
<seg id="239">  Like this is a painting of a snake in a box.  </seg>
<seg id="240">  So you open the box and you think, "Who, there's a snake in there."  </seg>
<seg id="241">  But it's actually a painting.  </seg>
<seg id="242">  So he makes these interesting conversations  about realism and mimicry  and our drive to be fooled by great camouflage.  </seg>
<seg id="243">  The next artist is Hazel Clausen.  </seg>
<seg id="244">  Hazel Clausen is an anthropologist who took a sabbatical  and decided, "You know, I would learn a lot about culture  if I created a culture that doesn't exist from scratch."  </seg>
<seg id="245">  So that's what she did.  </seg>
<seg id="246">  She created the Swiss people named the Uvulites,  and they have this distinctive yodeling song  that they use the uvula for.  </seg>
<seg id="247">  And also they reference how the uvula --  Everything they say is fallen  because of the forbidden fruit.  </seg>
<seg id="248">  And that's the symbol of their culture.  </seg>
<seg id="249">  And this is from a documentary  called "Sexual Practices and Populations Control  Among the Uvulites."  </seg>
<seg id="250">  This is a typical angora embroidery for them.  </seg>
<seg id="251">  This is one of their founders, Gert Schaeffer.  </seg>
<seg id="252">  And actually this is my Aunt Irene.  </seg>
<seg id="253">  It was so funny having a fake person  who was making fake things.  </seg>
<seg id="254">  And I crack up at this piece,  because when I see it I know that's French angora  and all antique German ribbons  and wool that I got in a Nebraska mill  and carried around for 10 years  and then antique Chinese skirts.  </seg>
<seg id="255">  The next is a collective of artists  called the Silver Dobermans.  </seg>
<seg id="256">  And their motto is to spread pragmatism  one person at a time.  </seg>
<seg id="257">  And they're really interested  in how over-coddled we've become.  </seg>
<seg id="258">  So this is one of their comments on how over-coddled we've become.  </seg>
<seg id="259">  And what they've done  is they put a warning sign on every single barb on this fence.  </seg>
<seg id="260">  And this is called "Horse Sense Fence."  </seg>
<seg id="261">  The next artist is K. M. Yoon,  a really interesting South Korean artist.  </seg>
<seg id="262">  And he's reworking a Confucian art tradition  of scholar stones.  </seg>
<seg id="263">  Next is Maynard Sipes.  </seg>
<seg id="264">  And I love Maynard Sipes,  but he's off in his own world,  and, bless his heart, he's so paranoid.  </seg>
<seg id="265">  Next is Roy Penig,  a really interesting Kentucky artist,  and he's the nicest guy.  </seg>
<seg id="266">  He even once traded a work of art for a block of government cheese  because the person wanted it so badly.  </seg>
<seg id="267">  Next is an Australian artist, Janeen Jackson,  and this is from a project of hers  called "What an Artwork Does When We're Not Watching."  </seg>
<seg id="268">  Next is by a Lithuanian fortune teller, Jurgi Petrauskas.  </seg>
<seg id="269">  Next is Ginger Cheshire.  </seg>
<seg id="270">  This is from a short film of hers called "The Last Person."  </seg>
<seg id="271">  And that's my cousin and my sister's dog, Gabby.  </seg>
<seg id="272">  The next, this is by Sam Sandy.  </seg>
<seg id="273">  He's an Australian Aboriginal elder,  and he's also an artist.  </seg>
<seg id="274">  And this is from a large traveling sculpture project  that he's doing.  </seg>
<seg id="275">  This is from Estelle Willoughsby.  </seg>
<seg id="276">  She heals with color.  </seg>
<seg id="277">  And she's one of the most prolific of all these hundred artists,  even though she's going to be 90 next year.  </seg>
<seg id="278">  This is by Z. Zhou,  and he's interested in stasis.  </seg>
<seg id="279">  Next is by Hilda Singh,  and she's doing a whole project called "Social Outfit."  </seg>
<seg id="280">  Next is by Vera Sokolova.  </seg>
<seg id="281">  And I have to say, Vera kind of scares me.  </seg>
<seg id="282">  You can't look her directly in the eyes,  because she's kind of scary.  </seg>
<seg id="283">  And it's good that she's not real;  she'd be mad that I said that.  </seg>
<seg id="284">  And she's an optometrist in St. Petersburg,  and she plays with optics.  </seg>
<seg id="285">  Next, this is by Thomas Swifton.  </seg>
<seg id="286">  This is from a short film, "Adventures of Skinny."  </seg>
<seg id="287">  And this is by Cicily Bennett,  and it's from a series of short films.  </seg>
<seg id="288">  And after this one, there's 77 other artists.  </seg>
<seg id="289">  And all together with those other 77 you're not seeing,  that's my biennial.  </seg>
<seg id="290">  Thank you. </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1178" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/joshua_walters_on_being_just_crazy_enough.html</url>
    <description>At TED's Full Spectrum Auditions, comedian Joshua Walters, who's bipolar, walks the line between mental illness and mental "skillness." In this funny, thought-provoking talk, he asks: What's the right balance between medicating craziness away and riding the manic edge of creativity and drive?</description>
    <keywords>Entertainment,brain,performance</keywords>
    <talkid>1178</talkid>
    <title>Joshua Walters: On being just crazy enough</title>
<seg id="291">  My name is Joshua Walters.  </seg>
<seg id="292">  I'm a performer.  </seg>
<seg id="293">  But as far as being a performer,  I'm also diagnosed  bipolar.  </seg>
<seg id="294">  I reframe that as a positive,  because the crazier I get onstage,  the more entertaining I become.  </seg>
<seg id="295">  When I was 16 in San Francisco,  I had my breakthrough manic episode  in which I thought I was Jesus Christ.  </seg>
<seg id="296">  Maybe you thought that was scary,  but actually there's no amount of drugs you can take  that can get you as high  as if you think you're Jesus Christ.  </seg>
<seg id="297">  I was sent to a place,  a psych ward,  and in the psych ward,  everyone is doing their own one-man show.  </seg>
<seg id="298">  There's no audience like this  to justify their rehearsal time.  </seg>
<seg id="299">  They're just practicing.  </seg>
<seg id="300">  One day they'll get here.  </seg>
<seg id="301">  Now when I got out,  I was diagnosed  and I was given medications  by a psychiatrist.  </seg>
<seg id="302">  "Okay, Josh, why don't we give you some --  why don't we give you some Zyprexa.  </seg>
<seg id="303">  Okay? Mmhmm?  </seg>
<seg id="304">  At least that's what it says on my pen."  </seg>
<seg id="305">  Some of you are in the field, I can see.  </seg>
<seg id="306">  I can feel your noise.  </seg>
<seg id="307">  The first half of high school  was the struggle of the manic episode,  and the second half  was the overmedications of these drugs,  where I was sleeping through high school.  </seg>
<seg id="308">  The second half was just one big nap, pretty much, in class.  </seg>
<seg id="309">  When I got out  I had a choice.  </seg>
<seg id="310">  I could either deny  my mental illness  or embrace  my mental skillness.  </seg>
<seg id="311">  There's a movement going on right now  to reframe mental illness as a positive --  at least the hypomanic edge part of it.  </seg>
<seg id="312">  Now if you don't know what hypomania is,  it's like an engine that's out of control,  maybe a Ferrari engine, with no breaks.  </seg>
<seg id="313">  Many of the speakers here, many of you in the audience,  have that creative edge,  if you know what I'm talking about.  </seg>
<seg id="314">  You're driven to do something  that everyone has told you is impossible.  </seg>
<seg id="315">  And there's a book -- John Gartner.  </seg>
<seg id="316">  John Gartner wrote this book called "The Hypomanic Edge"  in which Christopher Columbus and Ted Turner and Steve Jobs  and all these business minds  have this edge to compete.  </seg>
<seg id="317">  A different book was written not too long ago  in the mid-90s  called "Touched With Fire" by Kay Redfield Jamison  in which it was looked at in a creative sense  in which Mozart and Beethoven and Van Gogh  all have this manic depression that they were suffering with.  </seg>
<seg id="318">  Some of them committed suicide.  </seg>
<seg id="319">  So it wasn't all  the good side of the illness.  </seg>
<seg id="320">  Now recently,  there's been development in this field.  </seg>
<seg id="321">  And there was an article written in the New York Times,  September 2010,  that stated:  "Just Manic Enough."  </seg>
<seg id="322">  Just be manic enough  in which investors who are looking for entrepreneurs  that have this kind of spectrum --  you know what I'm talking about --  not maybe full bipolar,  but they're in the bipolar spectrum --  where on one side,  maybe you think you're Jesus,  and on the other side  maybe they just make you a lot of money.  </seg>
<seg id="323">  Your call. Your call.  </seg>
<seg id="324">  And everyone's somewhere in the middle.  </seg>
<seg id="325">  Everyone's somewhere in the middle.  </seg>
<seg id="326">  So maybe, you know,  there's no such thing  as crazy,  and being diagnosed with a mental illness  doesn't mean you're crazy.  </seg>
<seg id="327">  But maybe it just means  you're more sensitive  to what most people can't see  or feel.  </seg>
<seg id="328">  Maybe no one's really crazy.  </seg>
<seg id="329">  Everyone is just a little bit mad.  </seg>
<seg id="330">  How much  depends on where you fall in the spectrum.  </seg>
<seg id="331">  How much  depends on how lucky you are.  </seg>
<seg id="332">  Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1181" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/dave_debronkart_meet_e_patient_dave.html</url>
    <description>When Dave deBronkart learned he had a rare and terminal cancer, he turned to a group of fellow patients online -- and found the medical treatment that saved his life. Now he calls on all patients to talk with one another, know their own health data, and make health care better one e-Patient at a time.</description>
    <keywords>Culture,Science,Technology,collaboration,data,health care</keywords>
    <talkid>1181</talkid>
    <title>Dave deBronkart: Meet e-Patient Dave</title>
<seg id="333">  It's an amazing thing that we're here to talk  about the year of patients rising.  </seg>
<seg id="334">  You heard stories earlier today  about patients who are taking control of their cases,  patients who are saying, "You know what, I know what the odds are,  but I'm going to go look for more information.  </seg>
<seg id="335">  I'm going to define  what the terms of my success are."  </seg>
<seg id="336">  I'm going to be sharing with you  how four years ago I almost died --  found out I was, in fact,  already almost dead.  </seg>
<seg id="337">  And what I then found out about what's called the e-patient movement --  I'll explain what that term means.  </seg>
<seg id="338">  I had been blogging under the name Patient Dave,  and when I discovered this,  I just renamed myself e-Patient Dave.  </seg>
<seg id="339">  Regarding the word "patient,"  when I first started a few years ago  getting involved in health care  and attending meetings as just a casual observer,  I noticed that people would talk about patients  as if it was somebody who's not in the room here,  somebody out there.  </seg>
<seg id="340">  Some of our talks today, we still act like that.  </seg>
<seg id="341">  But I'm here to tell you,  "patient" is not a third-person word.  </seg>
<seg id="342">  You, yourself,  will find yourself in a hospital bed --  or your mother, your child --  there are heads nodding, people who say, "Yes, I know exactly what you mean."  </seg>
<seg id="343">  So when you hear what I'm going to talk about here today,  first of all, I want to say  that I am here on behalf  of all the patients that I have ever met,  all the ones I haven't met.  </seg>
<seg id="344">  This is about letting patients play a more active role  in helping health care, in fixing health care.  </seg>
<seg id="345">  One of the senior doctors at my hospital,  Charlie Safran, and his colleague, Warner Slack,  have been saying for decades  that the most underutilized resource in all of health care  is the patient.  </seg>
<seg id="346">  They have been saying that since the 1970s.  </seg>
<seg id="347">  Now I'm going to step back in history.  </seg>
<seg id="348">  This is from July, 1969.  </seg>
<seg id="349">  I was a freshman in college,  and this was when we first landed on the Moon.  </seg>
<seg id="350">  And it was the first time  we had ever seen from another surface --  that's the place where you and I are right now,  where we live.  </seg>
<seg id="351">  The world was changing.  </seg>
<seg id="352">  It was about to change in ways that nobody could foresee.  </seg>
<seg id="353">  A few weeks later,  Woodstock happened.  </seg>
<seg id="354">  Three days of fun and music.  </seg>
<seg id="355">  Here, just for historical authenticity,  is a picture of me in that year.  </seg>
<seg id="356">  Yeah, the wavy hair, the blue eyes --  it was really something.  </seg>
<seg id="357">  That Fall of 1969,  the Whole Earth Catalog came out.  </seg>
<seg id="358">  It was a hippie journal of self-sufficiency.  </seg>
<seg id="359">  We think of hippies of being just hedonists,  but there's a very strong component -- I was in that movement --  a very strong component  of being responsible for yourself.  </seg>
<seg id="360">  This book's title's subtitle  is: "Access to Tools."  </seg>
<seg id="361">  And it talked about how to build your own house,  how to grow your own food, all kinds of things.  </seg>
<seg id="362">  In the 1980s,  this doctor, Tom Ferguson,  was the medical editor of the Whole Earth Catalog.  </seg>
<seg id="363">  And he saw that the great majority  of what we do in medicine and health care  is taking care of ourselves.  </seg>
<seg id="364">  In fact, he said it was 70 to 80 percent  of how we actually take care of our bodies.  </seg>
<seg id="365">  Well he also saw  that when health care turns to medical care  because of a more serious disease,  the key thing that holds us back is access to information.  </seg>
<seg id="366">  And when the Web came along, that changed everything,  because not only could we find information,  we could find other people like ourselves  who could gather, who could bring us information.  </seg>
<seg id="367">  And he coined this term e-Patients --  equipped, engaged, empowered, enabled.  </seg>
<seg id="368">  Obviously at this stage of life  he was in a somewhat more dignified form than he was back then.  </seg>
<seg id="369">  Now I was an engaged patient  long before I ever heard of the term.  </seg>
<seg id="370">  In 2006, I went to my doctor for a regular physical,  and I had said, "I have a sore shoulder."  </seg>
<seg id="371">  Well, I got an X-ray,  and the next morning --  you may have noticed, those of you who have been through a medical crisis  will understand this.  </seg>
<seg id="372">  This morning, some of the speakers  named the date when they found out about their condition.  </seg>
<seg id="373">  For me, it was 9:00 AM  on January 3, 2007.  </seg>
<seg id="374">  I was at the office; my desk was clean;  I had the blue partition carpet on the walls.  </seg>
<seg id="375">  The phone rang and it was my doctor.  </seg>
<seg id="376">  He said, "Dave, I pulled up the X-ray image  on the screen on the computer at home."  </seg>
<seg id="377">  He said, "Your shoulder's going to be fine,  but Dave, there's something in your lung."  </seg>
<seg id="378">  And if you look in that red oval,  that shadow was not supposed to be there.  </seg>
<seg id="379">  To make a long story short,  I said, "So you need me to get back in there?"  </seg>
<seg id="380">  He said, "Yeah, we're going to need to do a CT scan of your chest."  </seg>
<seg id="381">  And in parting I said, "Is there anything I should do?"  </seg>
<seg id="382">  He said -- think about this one.  </seg>
<seg id="383">  This is the advice your doctor gives you.  </seg>
<seg id="384">  "Just go home and have a glass of wine with your wife."  </seg>
<seg id="385">  I went in for the CAT scan,  and it turns out there were five of these things in both my lungs.  </seg>
<seg id="386">  So at that point we knew that it was cancer.  </seg>
<seg id="387">  We knew it wasn't lung cancer.  </seg>
<seg id="388">  That meant it was metastasized from somewhere.  </seg>
<seg id="389">  The question was, where from?  </seg>
<seg id="390">  So I went in for an ultrasound.  </seg>
<seg id="391">  I got to do what many women have --  the jelly on the belly and bzzzz.  </seg>
<seg id="392">  My wife came with me.  </seg>
<seg id="393">  She's a veterinarian,  so she's seen lots of ultrasounds.  </seg>
<seg id="394">  I mean, she knows I'm not a dog.  </seg>
<seg id="395">  But what we saw -- this is an MRI image.  </seg>
<seg id="396">  This is much sharper than an ultrasound would be.  </seg>
<seg id="397">  What we saw in that kidney  was that big blob there.  </seg>
<seg id="398">  And there were actually two of these.  </seg>
<seg id="399">  One was growing out the front and it had already erupted,  and it latched onto the bowel.  </seg>
<seg id="400">  One was growing out the back, and it attached to the soleus muscle,  which is a big muscle in the back that I'd never heard of,  but all of a sudden I cared about it.  </seg>
<seg id="401">  I went home.  </seg>
<seg id="402">  Now I've been Googling -- I've been online since 1989 on Compuserv.  </seg>
<seg id="403">  I went home, and I know you can't read the details here;  that's not important.  </seg>
<seg id="404">  My point is I went to a respected medical website,  WebMD,  because I know how to filter out junk.  </seg>
<seg id="405">  I also found my wife online.  </seg>
<seg id="406">  Before I met her,  I went through some suboptimal search results.  </seg>
<seg id="407">  So I looked for quality information.  </seg>
<seg id="408">  There's so much about trust --  what sources of information can we trust?  </seg>
<seg id="409">  Where does my body end  and an invader start?  </seg>
<seg id="410">  And cancer, a tumor, is something you grow out of your own tissue.  </seg>
<seg id="411">  How does that happen?  </seg>
<seg id="412">  Where does medical ability  end and start?  </seg>
<seg id="413">  Well, so what I read on WebMD:  "The prognosis is poor  for progressing renal cell cancer.  </seg>
<seg id="414">  Almost all patients are incurable."  </seg>
<seg id="415">  I've been online long enough to know  if I don't like the first results I get,  I go look for more.  </seg>
<seg id="416">  And what I found was on other websites,  even by the third page of Google results,  "Outlook is bleak",  "Prognosis is grim."  </seg>
<seg id="417">  And I'm thinking, "What the heck?"  </seg>
<seg id="418">  I didn't feel sick at all.  </seg>
<seg id="419">  I mean, I'd been getting tired in the evening,  but I was 56 years-old.  </seg>
<seg id="420">  I was slowly losing weight,  but for me, that was what the doctor told me to do.  </seg>
<seg id="421">  It was really something.  </seg>
<seg id="422">  And this is the diagram of stage four kidney cancer  from the drug I eventually got.  </seg>
<seg id="423">  Totally by coincidence, there's that thing in my lung.  </seg>
<seg id="424">  In the left femur, the left thigh bone, there's another one.  </seg>
<seg id="425">  I had one. My leg eventually snapped.  </seg>
<seg id="426">  I fainted and landed on it, and it broke.  </seg>
<seg id="427">  There's one in the skull,  and then just for good measure, I had these other tumors --  including, by the time my treatment started,  one was growing out of my tongue.  </seg>
<seg id="428">  I had kidney cancer growing out of my tongue.  </seg>
<seg id="429">  And what I read was that my median survival  was 24 weeks.  </seg>
<seg id="430">  This was bad.  </seg>
<seg id="431">  I was facing the grave.  </seg>
<seg id="432">  I thought, "What's my mother's face going to look like  on the day of my funeral?"  </seg>
<seg id="433">  I had to sit down with my daughter  and say, "Here's the situation."  </seg>
<seg id="434">  Her boyfriend was with her.  </seg>
<seg id="435">  I said, "I don't want you guys to get married prematurely  just so you can do it while dad's still alive."  </seg>
<seg id="436">  It's really serious.  </seg>
<seg id="437">  Because if you wonder why patients are motivated and want to help,  think about this.  </seg>
<seg id="438">  Well, my doctor prescribed a patient community,  Acor.org,  a network of cancer patients, of all amazing things.  </seg>
<seg id="439">  Very quickly they told me,  "Kidney cancer is an uncommon disease.  </seg>
<seg id="440">  Get yourself to a specialist center.  </seg>
<seg id="441">  There is no cure, but there's something that sometimes works --  it usually doesn't --  called high-dosage interleukin.  </seg>
<seg id="442">  Most hospitals don't offer it,  so they won't even tell you it exists.  </seg>
<seg id="443">  And don't let them give you anything else first.  </seg>
<seg id="444">  And by the way, here are four doctors  in your part of the United States who offer it and their phone numbers.  </seg>
<seg id="445">  How amazing is that?  </seg>
<seg id="446">  Here's the thing.  </seg>
<seg id="447">  Here we are, four years later,  you can't find a website that gives patients that information.  </seg>
<seg id="448">  Government approved, American Cancer Society,  but patients know what patients want to know.  </seg>
<seg id="449">  It's the power of patient networks.  </seg>
<seg id="450">  This amazing substance --  again I mentioned, where does my body end?  </seg>
<seg id="451">  My oncologist and I talk a lot these days,  because I try to keep my talks technically accurate.  </seg>
<seg id="452">  And he said, "You know, the immune system  is good at detecting invaders --  bacteria coming from outside --  but when it's your own tissue that you've grown,  it's a whole different thing."  </seg>
<seg id="453">  And I went through a mental exercise actually,  because I started a patient support community of my own  on a website,  and one of my friends, one of my relatives actually,  said, "Look, Dave, who grew this thing?  </seg>
<seg id="454">  Are you going to set yourself up  as mentally attacking yourself?"  </seg>
<seg id="455">  So we went into it.  </seg>
<seg id="456">  And the story of how all that happens is in this book.  </seg>
<seg id="457">  Anyway, this is the way the numbers unfolded.  </seg>
<seg id="458">  Me being me, I put the numbers from my hospital's website  from my tumor sizes into a spreadsheet.  </seg>
<seg id="459">  Don't worry about the numbers.  </seg>
<seg id="460">  You see, that's the immune system.  </seg>
<seg id="461">  Amazing thing, those two yellow lines  are where I got the two doses of interleukin  two months apart.  </seg>
<seg id="462">  And look at how the tumor sizes plummeted in between.  </seg>
<seg id="463">  Just incredible.  </seg>
<seg id="464">  Who knows what we'll be able to do when we learn to make more use of it.  </seg>
<seg id="465">  The punch line is that a year and a half later,  I was there when this magnificent young woman, my daughter,  got married.  </seg>
<seg id="466">  And when she came down those steps,  and it was just her and me for that moment,  I was so glad that she didn't have to say to her mother,  "I wish Dad could have been here."  </seg>
<seg id="467">  And this is what we're doing  when we make health care better.  </seg>
<seg id="468">  Now I want to talk briefly about a couple of other patients  who are doing everything in their power to improve health care.  </seg>
<seg id="469">  This is Regina Holliday,  a painter in Washington D.C.,  whose husband died of kidney cancer a year after my disease.  </seg>
<seg id="470">  She's painting here a mural  of his horrible final weeks in the hospital.  </seg>
<seg id="471">  One of the things that she discovered  was that her husband's medical record  in this paper folder  was just disorganized.  </seg>
<seg id="472">  And she thought, "You know, if I have a nutrition facts label  on the side of a cereal box,  why can't there be something that simple  telling every new nurse who comes on duty,  every new doctor,  the basics about my husband's condition?"  </seg>
<seg id="473">  So she painted this medical facts mural  with a nutrition label,  something like that,  in a diagram of him.  </seg>
<seg id="474">  She then, last year, painted this diagram.  </seg>
<seg id="475">  She studied health care like me.  </seg>
<seg id="476">  She came to realize that there were a lot of people  who'd written patient advocate books  that you just don't hear about at medical conferences.  </seg>
<seg id="477">  Patients are such an underutilized resource.  </seg>
<seg id="478">  Well as it says in my introduction,  I've got somewhat know for saying that patients should have access to their data.  </seg>
<seg id="479">  And I actually said at one conference a couple of years ago,  "Give me my damn data,  because you people can't be trusted to keep it clean."  </seg>
<seg id="480">  And hear she has our dammed data --  it's a pun --  which is starting to break out, starting to break through --  the water symbolizes our data.  </seg>
<seg id="481">  And in fact, I want to do a little something improvisational for you here.  </seg>
<seg id="482">  There's a guy on Twitter that I know,  a health IT guy outside Boston,  and he wrote the e-Patient rap.  </seg>
<seg id="483">  And it goes like this.  </seg>
<seg id="484">   Gimme my damn data    I want to be an e-Patient just like Dave    Gimme my damn data, cuz it's my life to save   Now I'm not going to go any further.  </seg>
<seg id="485">  Well thank you. That shot the timing.  </seg>
<seg id="486">  Think about the possibility,  why is it that iPhones and iPads  advance far faster  than the health tools that are available to you  to help take care of your family?  </seg>
<seg id="487">  Here's a website, VisibleBody.com,  that I stumbled across.  </seg>
<seg id="488">  And I thought, "You know, I wonder what my soleus muscle is?"  </seg>
<seg id="489">  So you can click on things and remove it.  </seg>
<seg id="490">  And I saw, "Aha, that's the kidney and the soleus muscle."  </seg>
<seg id="491">  And I was rotating it in 3D  and saying, "I understand now."  </seg>
<seg id="492">  And then I realized it reminded me of Google Earth,  where you can fly to any address.  </seg>
<seg id="493">  And I thought, "Why not take this  and connect it to my digital scan data  and have Google Earth for my body?"  </seg>
<seg id="494">  What did Google come out with this year?  </seg>
<seg id="495">  Now there's Google Body browser.  </seg>
<seg id="496">  But you see, it's still generic.  </seg>
<seg id="497">  It's not my data.  </seg>
<seg id="498">  But if we can get that data out from behind the dam  so software innovators can pounce on it,  the way software innovators like to do,  who knows what we'll be able to come up with.  </seg>
<seg id="499">  One final story: this is Kelly Young,  a rheumatoid arthritis patient  from Florida.  </seg>
<seg id="500">  This is a live story  unfolding just in the last few weeks.  </seg>
<seg id="501">  RA patients, as they call themselves --  her blog is RA Warrior --  have a big problem  because 40 percent of them have no visible symptoms.  </seg>
<seg id="502">  And that makes it just really hard to tell how the disease is going.  </seg>
<seg id="503">  And some doctors think, "Yeah right, you're really in pain."  </seg>
<seg id="504">  Well she found, through her online research,  a nuclear bone scan  that's usually used for cancer,  but it can also reveal inflammation.  </seg>
<seg id="505">  And she saw  that if there is no inflammation  then the scan is a uniform gray.  </seg>
<seg id="506">  So she took it.  </seg>
<seg id="507">  And the radiologist report said, "No cancer found."  </seg>
<seg id="508">  Well that's not what he was supposed to do with it.  </seg>
<seg id="509">  So she had it read again, she wanted to have it read again,  and her doctor fired her.  </seg>
<seg id="510">  She pulled up the CD.  </seg>
<seg id="511">  He said, "If you don't want to follow my instructions,  go away."  </seg>
<seg id="512">  So she pulled up the CD of the scan images,  and look at all those hot spots.  </seg>
<seg id="513">  And she's now actively engaged on her blog  in looking for assistance in getting better care.  </seg>
<seg id="514">  See, that is an empowered patient -- no medical training.  </seg>
<seg id="515">  We are, you are,  the most underused resource in health care.  </seg>
<seg id="516">  What she was able to do  was because she had access to the raw data.  </seg>
<seg id="517">  How big a deal was this?  </seg>
<seg id="518">  Well at TED2009,  Tim Berners-Lee himself, inventor of the Web, gave a talk  where he said the next big thing  is not to have your browser go out  and find other people's articles about the data,  but the raw data.  </seg>
<seg id="519">  And he got them chanting by the end of the talk,  "Raw data now.  </seg>
<seg id="520">  Raw data now."  </seg>
<seg id="521">  And I ask you,  three words, please, to improve health care:  let patients help.  </seg>
<seg id="522">  Let patients help.  </seg>
<seg id="523">  Let patients help.  </seg>
<seg id="524">  Let patients help.  </seg>
<seg id="525">  Thank you.  </seg>
<seg id="526">  For all the patients around the world  watching this on the webcast,  God bless you, everyone -- let patients help.  </seg>
<seg id="527">  And bless yourself. Thank you very much.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1174" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/bill_ford_a_future_beyond_traffic_gridlock.html</url>
    <description>Bill Ford is a car guy -- his great-grandfather was Henry Ford, and he grew up inside the massive Ford Motor Co. So when he worries about cars' impact on the environment, and about our growing global gridlock problem, it's worth a listen. His vision for the future of mobility includes "smart roads," even smarter public transport and going green like never before.</description>
    <keywords>Design,Technology,cars,mobility</keywords>
    <talkid>1174</talkid>
    <title>Bill Ford: A future beyond traffic gridlock</title>
<seg id="528">  By birth and by choice,  I've been involved with the auto industry my entire life,  and for the past 30 years,  I've worked at Ford Motor Company.  </seg>
<seg id="529">  And for most of those years,  I've worried about,  how am I going to sell more cars and trucks?  </seg>
<seg id="530">  But today I worry about,  what if all we do is sell more cars and trucks?  </seg>
<seg id="531">  What happens  when the number of vehicles on the road doubles, triples,  or even quadruples?  </seg>
<seg id="532">  My life is guided by two great passions,  and the first is automobiles.  </seg>
<seg id="533">  I literally grew up with the Ford Motor Company.  </seg>
<seg id="534">  I thought it was so cool as a little boy  when my dad would bring home the latest Ford or Lincoln  and leave it in the driveway.  </seg>
<seg id="535">  And I decided about that time, about age 10,  that it would be really cool if I was a test driver.  </seg>
<seg id="536">  So my parents would go to dinner.  </seg>
<seg id="537">  They'd sit down, I'd sneak out of the house.  </seg>
<seg id="538">  I'd jump behind the wheel and take the new model around the driveway,  and it was a blast.  </seg>
<seg id="539">  And that went on for about two years,  until -- I think I was about 12 --  my dad brought home  a Lincoln Mark III.  </seg>
<seg id="540">  And it was snowing that day.  </seg>
<seg id="541">  So he and mom went to dinner.  </seg>
<seg id="542">  And I snuck out  and thought it'd be really cool to do donuts  or even some figure-eights in the snow.  </seg>
<seg id="543">  My dad finished dinner early that evening.  </seg>
<seg id="544">  And he was walking to the front hall  and out the front door  just about the same time I hit some ice  and met him at the front door with the car --  and almost ended up in the front hall.  </seg>
<seg id="545">  So it kind of cooled my test driving for a little while.  </seg>
<seg id="546">  But I really began to love cars then.  </seg>
<seg id="547">  And my first car was a 1975 electric-green Mustang.  </seg>
<seg id="548">  And even though the color was pretty hideous,  I did love the car,  and it really cemented my love affair with cars  that's continued on to this day.  </seg>
<seg id="549">  But cars are really more than a passion of mine;  they quite literally in my blood.  </seg>
<seg id="550">  My great grandfather was Henry Ford,  and on my mother's side,  my great grandfather was Harvey Firestone.  </seg>
<seg id="551">  So when I was born,  I guess you could say expectations were kind of high for me.  </seg>
<seg id="552">  But my great grandfather, Henry Ford,  really believed that the mission of the Ford Motor Company  was to make people's lives better  and make cars affordable so that everyone could have them.  </seg>
<seg id="553">  Because he believed that, with mobility,  comes freedom and progress.  </seg>
<seg id="554">  And that's a belief that I share.  </seg>
<seg id="555">  My other great passion is the environment.  </seg>
<seg id="556">  And as a young boy, I used to go up to Northern Michigan  and fish in the rivers that Hemingway fished in  and then later wrote about.  </seg>
<seg id="557">  And it really struck me  as the years went by,  in a very negative way,  when I would go to some stream that I'd loved,  and was used to walking through this field  that was once filled with fireflies,  and now had a strip mall or a bunch of condos on it.  </seg>
<seg id="558">  And so even at a young age,  that really resonated with me.  </seg>
<seg id="559">  And the whole notion of environmental preservation,  at a very basic level, sunk in with me.  </seg>
<seg id="560">  As a high-schooler, I started to read  authors like Thoreau and Aldo Leopold  and Edward Abbey.  </seg>
<seg id="561">  And I really began to develop  a deeper appreciation of the natural world.  </seg>
<seg id="562">  But it never really occurred to me  that my love of cars and trucks  would ever be in conflict with nature.  </seg>
<seg id="563">  And that was true  until I got to college.  </seg>
<seg id="564">  And when I got to college, you can imagine my surprise  when I would go to class  and a number of my professors would say  that Ford Motor Company and my family  was everything that was wrong with our country.  </seg>
<seg id="565">  They thought that we were more interested, as an industry,  in profits, rather than progress,  and that we filled the skies with smog --  and frankly, we were the enemy.  </seg>
<seg id="566">  I joined Ford after college,  after some soul searching  whether or not this is really the right thing to do.  </seg>
<seg id="567">  But I decided that I wanted to go  and see if I could affect change there.  </seg>
<seg id="568">  And as I look back over 30 years ago,  it was a little naive to think at that age  that I could, but I wanted to.  </seg>
<seg id="569">  And I really discovered  that my professors weren't completely wrong.  </seg>
<seg id="570">  In fact, when I got back to Detroit,  my environmental leanings weren't exactly embraced  by those in my own company,  and certainly by those in the industry.  </seg>
<seg id="571">  I had some very interesting conversations,  as you can imagine.  </seg>
<seg id="572">  There were some within Ford  who believed that all this ecological nonsense  should just disappear  and that I needed to stop hanging out  with "environmental wackos".  </seg>
<seg id="573">  I was considered a radical.  </seg>
<seg id="574">  And I'll never forget the day I was called in by a member of top management  and told to stop associating  with any known or suspected environmentalists.  </seg>
<seg id="575">  Of course, I had no intention of doing that.  </seg>
<seg id="576">  And I kept speaking out about the environment.  </seg>
<seg id="577">  And it really was the topic  that we now today sustainability.  </seg>
<seg id="578">  And in time, my views went from controversial  to more or less consensus today.  </seg>
<seg id="579">  I mean, I think most people in the industry  understand that we've got to get on with it.  </seg>
<seg id="580">  And the good news is today we are tackling the big issues,  of cars and the environment --  not only at Ford, but really as an industry.  </seg>
<seg id="581">  We're pushing fuel efficiency to new heights.  </seg>
<seg id="582">  And with new technology,  we're reducing -- and I believe, someday will eliminate --  CO2 emissions.  </seg>
<seg id="583">  We're starting to sell electric cars, which is great.  </seg>
<seg id="584">  We're developing alternative power trains  that are going to make cars affordable  in every sense of the word --  economically, socially  and environmentally.  </seg>
<seg id="585">  And actually, although we've got a long way to go  and a lot of work to do,  I can see the day where my two great passions --  cars and the environment --  actually come into harmony.  </seg>
<seg id="586">  But unfortunately,  as we're on our way to solving one monstrous problem --  and as I said, we're not there yet; we've got a lot of work to do,  but I can see where we will --  but even as we're in the process of doing that,  another huge problem is looming,  and people aren't noticing.  </seg>
<seg id="587">  And that is the freedom of mobility  that my great grandfather brought to people  is now being threatened, just as the environment is.  </seg>
<seg id="588">  The problem, put in its simplest terms,  is one of mathematics.  </seg>
<seg id="589">  Today there are approximately 6.8 billion people in the world.  </seg>
<seg id="590">  And within our lifetime, that number's going to grow  to about nine billion.  </seg>
<seg id="591">  And at that population level,  our planet will be dealing with the limits of growth.  </seg>
<seg id="592">  And with that growth  comes some severe practical problems,  one of which is our transportation system  simply won't be able to deal with it.  </seg>
<seg id="593">  When we look at the population growth in terms of cars,  it becomes even clearer.  </seg>
<seg id="594">  Today there are about 800 million cars on the road worldwide.  </seg>
<seg id="595">  But with more people  and greater prosperity around the world,  that number's going to grow  to between two and four billion cars by mid century.  </seg>
<seg id="596">  And this is going to create the kind of global gridlock  that the world has never seen before.  </seg>
<seg id="597">  Now think about the impact  that this is going to have on our daily lives.  </seg>
<seg id="598">  Today the average American  spends about a week a year  stuck in traffic jams.  </seg>
<seg id="599">  And that's a huge waste of time and resources.  </seg>
<seg id="600">  But that's nothing compared  to what's going on  in the nations that are growing the fastest.  </seg>
<seg id="601">  Today the average driver in Beijing  has a five-hour commute.  </seg>
<seg id="602">  And last summer -- many of you probably saw this --  there was a hundred-mile traffic jam  that took 11 days to clear in China.  </seg>
<seg id="603">  In the decades to come,  75 percent of the world's population  will live in cities,  and 50 of those cities  will be of 10 million people or more.  </seg>
<seg id="604">  So you can see the size of the issue that we're facing.  </seg>
<seg id="605">  When you factor in population growth,  it's clear that mobility model that we have today  simply will not work tomorrow.  </seg>
<seg id="606">  Frankly, four billion clean cars on the road  are still four billion cars.  </seg>
<seg id="607">  And a traffic jam with no emissions  is still a traffic jam.  </seg>
<seg id="608">  So, if we make no changes today,  what does tomorrow look like?  </seg>
<seg id="609">  Well I think you probably already have the picture.  </seg>
<seg id="610">  Traffic jams are just a symptom of this challenge,  and they're really very, very inconvenient,  but that's all they are.  </seg>
<seg id="611">  But the bigger issue  is that global gridlock  is going to stifle economic growth  and our ability to deliver  food and health care,  particularly to people that live in city centers.  </seg>
<seg id="612">  And our quality of life is going to be severely compromised.  </seg>
<seg id="613">  So what's going to solve this?  </seg>
<seg id="614">  Well the answer isn't going to be more of the same.  </seg>
<seg id="615">  My great grandfather once said  before he invented the Model T,  "If I had asked people then what they wanted,  they would have answered,  'We want faster horses.'"  So the answer to more cars  is simply not to have more roads.  </seg>
<seg id="616">  When America began moving West,  we didn't add more wagon trains,  we built railroads.  </seg>
<seg id="617">  And to connect our country after World War II,  we didn't build more two-lane highways,  we built the interstate highway system.  </seg>
<seg id="618">  Today we need that same leap in thinking  for us to create a viable future.  </seg>
<seg id="619">  We are going to build smart cars,  but we also need to build  smart roads, smart parking,  smart public transportation systems and more.  </seg>
<seg id="620">  We don't want to waste our time  sitting in traffic, sitting at toll booths  or looking for parking spots.  </seg>
<seg id="621">  We need an integrated system  that uses real time data  to optimize personal mobility on a massive scale  without hassle or compromises for travelers.  </seg>
<seg id="622">  And frankly, that's the kind of system  that's going to make the future of personal mobility sustainable.  </seg>
<seg id="623">  Now the good news is some of this work has already begun  in different parts of the world.  </seg>
<seg id="624">  The city of Masdar in Abu Dhabi  uses driverless electric vehicles  that can communicate with one another,  and they go underneath the city streets.  </seg>
<seg id="625">  And up above, you've got a series of pedestrian walkways.  </seg>
<seg id="626">  On New York City's 34th St.,  gridlock will soon be replaced  with a connected system  of vehicle-specific corridors.  </seg>
<seg id="627">  Pedestrian zones and dedicated traffic lanes are going to be created,  and all of this will cut down the average rush hour commute  to get across town in New York  from about an hour today at rush hour  to about 20 minutes.  </seg>
<seg id="628">  Now if you look at Hong Kong,  they have a very interesting system called Octopus there.  </seg>
<seg id="629">  It's a system that really ties together  all the transportation assets  into a single payment system.  </seg>
<seg id="630">  So parking garages, buses, trains,  they all operate within the same system.  </seg>
<seg id="631">  Now shared car services  are also springing up around the world.  </seg>
<seg id="632">  And these efforts, I think, are great.  </seg>
<seg id="633">  They're relieving congestion,  and they're frankly starting to save some fuel.  </seg>
<seg id="634">  These are all really good ideas  that will move us forward.  </seg>
<seg id="635">  But what really inspires me  is what's going to be possible  when our cars can begin talking to each other.  </seg>
<seg id="636">  Very soon, the same systems that we use today  to bring music and entertainment  and GPS information into our vehicles  are going to be used to create  a smart vehicle network.  </seg>
<seg id="637">  Every morning I drive about 30 miles  from my home in Ann Arbor to my office in Dearborn, Michigan.  </seg>
<seg id="638">  And every night I go home,  my commute is a total crap shoot.  </seg>
<seg id="639">  And I often have to leave the freeway  and look for different ways  for me to try and make it home.  </seg>
<seg id="640">  But very soon we're going to see the days  when cars are essentially talking to each other.  </seg>
<seg id="641">  So if the car ahead of me on I-94 hits traffic,  it will immediately alert my car  and tell my car to reroute itself  to get me home in the best possible way.  </seg>
<seg id="642">  And these systems are being tested right now,  and frankly they're going to be ready for prime time pretty soon.  </seg>
<seg id="643">  But the potential of a connected car network  is almost limitless.  </seg>
<seg id="644">  one day very soon,  you're going to be able to plan a trip downtown  and your car will be connected to a smart parking system.  </seg>
<seg id="645">  So you get in your car,  and as you get in your car,  your car will reserve you a parking spot before you arrive --  no more driving around looking for one,  which frankly is one of the biggest users of fuel  in today's cars in urban areas  is looking for parking spots.  </seg>
<seg id="646">  Or think about being in New York City  and tracking down an intelligent cab on your smart phone  so you don't have to wait in the cold to hail one.  </seg>
<seg id="647">  Or being at a future TED Conference  and having your car  talk to the calendars of everybody here  and telling you all the best route to take home  and when you should leave,  so that you can all arrive at your next destination on time.  </seg>
<seg id="648">  This is the kind of technology  that will merge millions of individual vehicles  into a single system.  </seg>
<seg id="649">  So I think it's clear we have the beginnings of a solution  to this enormous problem.  </seg>
<seg id="650">  But as we found out with addressing CO2 issues,  and also fossil fuels,  there is no one silver bullet.  </seg>
<seg id="651">  The solution is not going to be  more cars, more roads or a new rail system;  it can only be found, I believe,  in a global network  of interconnected solutions.  </seg>
<seg id="652">  Now I know we can develop the technology  that's going to make this work,  but we've got to be willing to get out there  and seek out the solutions --  whether that means vehicle sharing or public transportation  or some other way we haven't even thought of yet,  our overall transportation mix and infrastructure  must support all the future options.  </seg>
<seg id="653">  We need our best and our brightest  to start entertaining this issue.  </seg>
<seg id="654">  Companies, entrepreneurs, venture capitalists,  they all need to understand  this is a huge business opportunity,  as well as an enormous social problem.  </seg>
<seg id="655">  And just as these groups  embrace the green energy challenge --  and it's really been amazing to me to watch  how much brain power, how much money  and how much serious thought  has, really over the last three years,  just poured into the green energy field.  </seg>
<seg id="656">  We need that same kind of passion and energy  to attack global gridlock.  </seg>
<seg id="657">  But we need people like all of you in this room,  leading thinkers.  </seg>
<seg id="658">  I mean, frankly I need all of you  to think about how  you can help solve this huge issue.  </seg>
<seg id="659">  And we need people from all walks of life;  not just inventors, we need policymakers  and government officials  to also think about how they're going to respond to this challenge.  </seg>
<seg id="660">  This isn't going to be solved  by any one person or one group.  </seg>
<seg id="661">  It's going to really require a national energy policy,  frankly for each country,  because the solutions in each country are going to be different  based upon income levels, traffic jams  and also how integrated  the systems already are.  </seg>
<seg id="662">  But we need to get going, and we need to get going today.  </seg>
<seg id="663">  And we must have an infrastructure  that's designed to support  this flexible future.  </seg>
<seg id="664">  You know, we've come a long way.  </seg>
<seg id="665">  Since the Model T,  most people never traveled  more than 25 miles from home in their entire life time.  </seg>
<seg id="666">  And since then,  the automobile has allowed us the freedom  to choose where we live, where we work,  where we play  and frankly when we just go out and want to move around.  </seg>
<seg id="667">  We don't want to regress and lose that freedom.  </seg>
<seg id="668">  We're on our way to solving --  and as I said earlier, I know we've got a long way to go --  the one big issue that we're all focused on that threatens it,  and that's the environmental issue,  but I believe we all must turn  all of our effort and all of our ingenuity and determination  to help now solve this notion of global gridlock.  </seg>
<seg id="669">  Because in doing so,  we're going to preserve what we've really come to take for granted,  which is the freedom to move  and move very effortlessly around the world.  </seg>
<seg id="670">  And it frankly will enhance our quality of life  if we fix this.  </seg>
<seg id="671">  Because, if you can envision, as I do,  a future of zero emissions  and freedom to move around the country and around the world  like we take for granted today,  that's worth the hard work today  to preserve that for tomorrow.  </seg>
<seg id="672">  I believe we're at our best  when we're confronted with big issues.  </seg>
<seg id="673">  This is a big one, and it won't wait.  </seg>
<seg id="674">  So let's get started now.  </seg>
<seg id="675">  Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1182" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/robert_hammond_building_a_park_in_the_sky.html</url>
    <description>New York was planning to tear down the High Line, an abandoned elevated railroad in Manhattan, when Robert Hammond and a few friends suggested: Why not make it a park? He shares how it happened in this tale of local cultural activism.</description>
    <keywords>Arts,Culture,activism,cities</keywords>
    <talkid>1182</talkid>
    <title>Robert Hammond: Building a park in the sky</title>
<seg id="676">  The Highline  is an old, elevated rail line  that runs for a mile and a half right through Manhattan.  </seg>
<seg id="677">  And it was originally a freight line  that ran down 10th Ave.  </seg>
<seg id="678">  And it became known as "Death Avenue"  because so many people were run over by the trains  that the railroad hired a guy on horseback to run in front,  and he became known as the "West Side Cowboy."  </seg>
<seg id="679">  But even with a cowboy,  about one person a month  was killed and run over.  </seg>
<seg id="680">  So they elevated it.  </seg>
<seg id="681">  They built it 30 ft. in the air, right through the middle of the city.  </seg>
<seg id="682">  But with the rise of interstate trucking,  it was used less and less.  </seg>
<seg id="683">  And by 1980, the last train rode.  </seg>
<seg id="684">  It was a train loaded with frozen turkeys -- they say, at Thanksgiving --  from the meatpacking district.  </seg>
<seg id="685">  And then it was abandoned.  </seg>
<seg id="686">  And I live in the neighborhood,  and I first read about it in the New York Times,  in an article that said it was going to be demolished.  </seg>
<seg id="687">  And I assumed someone was working  to preserve it or save it  and I could volunteer,  but I realized no one was doing anything.  </seg>
<seg id="688">  I went to my first community board meeting --  which I'd never been to one before --  and sat next to another guy named Joshua David,  who's a travel writer.  </seg>
<seg id="689">  And at the end of the meeting, we realized  we were the only two people that were sort of interested in the project;  most people wanted to tear it down.  </seg>
<seg id="690">  So we exchanged business cards,  and we kept calling each other  and decided to start this organization,  Friends of the High Line.  </seg>
<seg id="691">  And the goal at first  was just saving it from demolition,  but then we also wanted to figure out what we could do with it.  </seg>
<seg id="692">  And what first attracted me, or interested me,  was this view from the street --  which is this steel structure,  sort of rusty,  this industrial relic.  </seg>
<seg id="693">  But when I went up on top,  it was a mile and a half of wildflowers  running right through the middle of Manhattan  with views of the Empire State Building  and the Statue of Liberty and the Hudson River.  </seg>
<seg id="694">  And that's really where we started,  the idea coalesced around, let's make this a park,  and let's have it be sort of inspired  by this wildscape.  </seg>
<seg id="695">  At the time, there was a lot of opposition.  </seg>
<seg id="696">  Mayor Giuliani wanted to tear it down.  </seg>
<seg id="697">  I'm going to fast-forward through a lot of lawsuits  and a lot of community engagement.  </seg>
<seg id="698">  Mayor Bloomberg came in office, he was very supportive,  but we still had to make the economic case.  </seg>
<seg id="699">  This was after 9/11;  the city was in tough times.  </seg>
<seg id="700">  So we commissioned an economic feasibility study  to try to make the case.  </seg>
<seg id="701">  And it turns out, we got those numbers wrong.  </seg>
<seg id="702">  We thought it would cost 100 million dollars to build.  </seg>
<seg id="703">  So far it's cost about 150 million.  </seg>
<seg id="704">  And the main case was,  this is going to make good economic sense for the city.  </seg>
<seg id="705">  So we said over a 20-year time period,  the value to the city in increased property values  and increased taxes  would be about 250 million.  </seg>
<seg id="706">  That was enough. It really got the city behind it.  </seg>
<seg id="707">  It turns out we were wrong on that.  </seg>
<seg id="708">  Now people estimate it's created about a half a billion dollars,  or will create about a half a billion dollars,  in tax revenues for the city.  </seg>
<seg id="709">  We did a design competition,  selected a design team.  </seg>
<seg id="710">  We worked with them to really create a design  that was inspired by that wildscape.  </seg>
<seg id="711">  There's three sections.  </seg>
<seg id="712">  We opened the fist section in 2009.  </seg>
<seg id="713">  It's been successful beyond our dreams.  </seg>
<seg id="714">  Last year we had about two million people,  which is about 10 times what we ever estimated.  </seg>
<seg id="715">  This is one of my favorite features in section one.  </seg>
<seg id="716">  It's this amphitheater right over 10th Ave.  </seg>
<seg id="717">  And the first section ends at 20th St. right now.  </seg>
<seg id="718">  The other thing, it's generated, obviously, a lot of economic value;  it's also inspired, I think, a lot of great architecture.  </seg>
<seg id="719">  There's a point, you can stand here  and see buildings by Frank Gehry,  Jean Nouvel, Shigeru Ban,  Neil Denari.  </seg>
<seg id="720">  And the Whitney is moving downtown  and is building their new museum right at the base of the High Line.  </seg>
<seg id="721">  And this has been designed by Renzo Piano.  </seg>
<seg id="722">  And they're going to break ground in May.  </seg>
<seg id="723">  And we've already started construction on section two.  </seg>
<seg id="724">  This is one of my favorite features,  this flyover where you're eight feet  off the surface of the High Line,  running through a canopy of trees.  </seg>
<seg id="725">  The High Line used to be covered in billboards,  and so we've taken a playful take  where, instead of framing advertisements,  it's going to frame people in views of the city.  </seg>
<seg id="726">  This was just installed last month.  </seg>
<seg id="727">  And then the last section was going to go around the rail yards,  which is the largest undeveloped site  in Manhattan.  </seg>
<seg id="728">  And the city has planned -- for better or for worse --  12 million square-feet of development  that the High Line is going to ring around.  </seg>
<seg id="729">  But what really, I think, makes the High Line special  is the people.  </seg>
<seg id="730">  And honestly, even though I love the designs that we were building,  I was always frightened that I wouldn't really love it,  because I fell in love with that wildscape --  and how could you recreate that magic?  </seg>
<seg id="731">  But what I found  is it's in the people and how they use it  that, to me, makes it so special.  </seg>
<seg id="732">  Just one quick example  is I realized right after we opened  that there were all these people holding hands on the High Line.  </seg>
<seg id="733">  And I realized New Yorkers don't hold hands;  we just don't do that outside.  </seg>
<seg id="734">  But you see that happening on the High Line,  and I think that's the power  that public space can have  to transform how people experience their city  and interact with each other.  </seg>
<seg id="735">  Thanks.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1183" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/matt_cutts_try_something_new_for_30_days.html</url>
    <description>Is there something you've always meant to do, wanted to do, but just ... haven't? Matt Cutts suggests: Try it for 30 days. This short, lighthearted talk offers a neat way to think about setting and achieving goals.</description>
    <keywords>Culture,success</keywords>
    <talkid>1183</talkid>
    <title>Matt Cutts: Try something new for 30 days</title>
<seg id="736">  A few years ago,  I felt like I was stuck in a rut,  so I decided to follow in the footsteps  of the great American philosopher, Morgan Spurlock,  and try something new for 30 days.  </seg>
<seg id="737">  The idea is actually pretty simple.  </seg>
<seg id="738">  Think about something you've always wanted to add to your life  and try it for the next 30 days.  </seg>
<seg id="739">  It turns out,  30 days is just about the right amount of time  to add a new habit or subtract a habit --  like watching the news --  from your life.  </seg>
<seg id="740">  There's a few things I learned while doing these 30-day challenges.  </seg>
<seg id="741">  The first was,  instead of the months flying by, forgotten,  the time was much more memorable.  </seg>
<seg id="742">  This was part of a challenge I did to take a picture everyday for a month.  </seg>
<seg id="743">  And I remember exactly where I was  and what I was doing that day.  </seg>
<seg id="744">  I also noticed  that as I started to do more and harder 30-day challenges,  my self-confidence grew.  </seg>
<seg id="745">  I went from desk-dwelling computer nerd  to the kind of guy who bikes to work --  for fun.  </seg>
<seg id="746">  Even last year, I ended up hiking up Mt. Kilimanjaro,  the highest mountain in Africa.  </seg>
<seg id="747">  I would never have been that adventurous  before I started my 30-day challenges.  </seg>
<seg id="748">  I also figured out  that if you really want something badly enough,  you can do anything for 30 days.  </seg>
<seg id="749">  Have you ever wanted to write a novel?  </seg>
<seg id="750">  Every November,  tens of thousands of people  try to write their own 50,000 word novel from scratch  in 30 days.  </seg>
<seg id="751">  It turns out, all you have to do  is write 1,667 words a day  for a month.  </seg>
<seg id="752">  So I did.  </seg>
<seg id="753">  By the way, the secret is not to go to sleep  until you've written your words for the day.  </seg>
<seg id="754">  You might be sleep-deprived,  but you'll finish your novel.  </seg>
<seg id="755">  Now is my book the next great American novel?  </seg>
<seg id="756">  No. I wrote it in a month.  </seg>
<seg id="757">  It's awful.  </seg>
<seg id="758">  But for the rest of my life,  if I meet john Hodgman at a TED party,  I don't have to say,  "I'm a computer scientist."  </seg>
<seg id="759">  No, no, if I want to I can say, "I'm a novelist."  </seg>
<seg id="760">  So here's one last thing I'd like to mention.  </seg>
<seg id="761">  I learned that when I made small, sustainable changes,  things I could keep doing,  they were more likely to stick.  </seg>
<seg id="762">  There's nothing wrong with big, crazy challenges.  </seg>
<seg id="763">  In fact, they're a ton of fun.  </seg>
<seg id="764">  But they're less likely to stick.  </seg>
<seg id="765">  When I gave up sugar for 30 days,  day 31 looked like this.  </seg>
<seg id="766">  So here's my question to you:  What are you waiting for?  </seg>
<seg id="767">  I guarantee you the next 30 days  are going to pass  whether you like it or not,  so why not think about something  you have always wanted to try  and give it a shot  for the next 30 days.  </seg>
<seg id="768">  Thanks.  </seg>
</doc>
<doc docid="1187" genre="lectures">
    <url>http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/nina_tandon_caring_for_cells.html</url>
    <description>Tissue engineer and TED Fellow Nina Tandon is growing artificial hearts and bones. To do that, she needs new ways of caring for artificially grown cells -- techniques she's developed by the simple but powerful method of copying their natural environments.</description>
    <keywords>Science,biology,biomimicry,biotech</keywords>
    <talkid>1187</talkid>
    <title>Nina Tandon: Caring for engineered tissue</title>
<seg id="769">  Good morning everybody.  </seg>
<seg id="770">  I work with really amazing  little itty bitty creatures called cells.  </seg>
<seg id="771">  And let me tell you what it's like  to grow these cells in the lab.  </seg>
<seg id="772">  I work in a lab where we take cells out of their native environment.  </seg>
<seg id="773">  We plate them into dishes  that we sometimes call petri dishes.  </seg>
<seg id="774">  And we feed them -- sterilly of course --  with what we call cell culture media -- which is like their food --  and we grow them in incubators.  </seg>
<seg id="775">  Why do I do this?  </seg>
<seg id="776">  We observe the cells in a plate,  and they're just on the surface.  </seg>
<seg id="777">  But what we're really trying to do in my lab  is to engineer tissues out of them.  </seg>
<seg id="778">  What does that even mean?  </seg>
<seg id="779">  Well it means growing an actual heart,  let's say,  or grow a piece of bone  that can be put into the body.  </seg>
<seg id="780">  Not only that, but they can also be used for disease models.  </seg>
<seg id="781">  And for this purpose, traditional cell culture techniques  just really aren't enough.  </seg>
<seg id="782">  The cells are kind of homesick;  the dish doesn't feel like their home.  </seg>
<seg id="783">  And so we need to do better at copying their natural environment  to get them to thrive.  </seg>
<seg id="784">  We call this the biomimetic paradigm --  copying nature in the lab.  </seg>
<seg id="785">  Let's take the example of the heart,  the topic of a lot of my research.  </seg>
<seg id="786">  What makes the heart unique?  </seg>
<seg id="787">  Well, the heart beats,  rhythmically, tirelessly, faithfully.  </seg>
<seg id="788">  We copy this in the lab  by outfitting cell culture systems with electrodes.  </seg>
<seg id="789">  These electrodes act like mini pacemakers  to get the cells to contract in the lab.  </seg>
<seg id="790">  What else do we know about the heart?  </seg>
<seg id="791">  Well heart cells are pretty greedy.  </seg>
<seg id="792">  Nature feeds the heart cells in your body  with a very, very dense blood supply.  </seg>
<seg id="793">  In the lab, we micro-pattern channels  in the biomaterials  on which we grow the cells.  </seg>
<seg id="794">  And this allows us to flow the cell culture media, the cells' food,  through the scaffolds where we're growing the cells --  a lot like what you might expect  from a capillary bed in the heart.  </seg>
<seg id="795">  So this brings me to lesson number one:  life can do a lot with very little.  </seg>
<seg id="796">  Let's take the example of electrical stimulation.  </seg>
<seg id="797">  Let's see how powerful just one of these essentials can be.  </seg>
<seg id="798">  On the left, we see a tiny piece of beating heart tissue  that I engineered from rat cells in the lab.  </seg>
<seg id="799">  It's about the size of a mini marshmallow.  </seg>
<seg id="800">  And after one week, it's beating.  </seg>
<seg id="801">  You can see it in the upper left-hand corner.  </seg>
<seg id="802">  But don't worry if you can't see it so well.  </seg>
<seg id="803">  It's amazing that these cells beat at all.  </seg>
<seg id="804">  But what's really amazing  is that the cells, when we electrically stimulate them  like with a pacemaker,  that they beat so much more.  </seg>
<seg id="805">  But that brings me to lesson number two:  cells do all the work.  </seg>
<seg id="806">  In a sense, tissue engineers have a bit of an identity crisis here,  because structural engineers  build bridges and big things,  computer engineers, computers,  but what we are doing  is actually building enabling technologies for the cells themselves.  </seg>
<seg id="807">  What does this mean for us?  </seg>
<seg id="808">  Let's do something really simple.  </seg>
<seg id="809">  Let's remind ourselves  that cells are not an abstract concept.  </seg>
<seg id="810">  Let's remember that our cells sustain our lives  in a very real way.  </seg>
<seg id="811">  "We are what we eat," could easily be described  as, "We are what our cells eat."  </seg>
<seg id="812">  And in the case of the flora in our gut,  these cells may not even be human.  </seg>
<seg id="813">  But it's also worth noting  that cells also mediate our experience of life.  </seg>
<seg id="814">  Behind every sound, sight, touch, taste and smell  is a corresponding set of cells  that receive this information  and interpret it for us.  </seg>
<seg id="815">  It begs the question:  shall we expand our sense of environmental stewardship  to include the ecosystem of our own bodies?  </seg>
<seg id="816">  I invite you to talk about this with me further,  and in the meantime, I wish you luck.  </seg>
<seg id="817">  May none of your non-cancer cells  become endangered species.  </seg>
<seg id="818">  Thank you.  </seg>
</doc>
</srcset>
</mteval>
